<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The garlande of godly flowers bewtifully adorned as most freshly they flourish in the gardeins of right faithfull Christian writers. Yéeldyng foorth a very comfortable sauour to the afflicted soule, wherby hée is salfly [sic] transported vnto the mercifull throne of the most glorious God. Carefully collected, and diligently digested into ordre, by Tho. Twyne, Gentleman. 1574.</title>
            <author>Twyne, Thomas, 1543-1613.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1574</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 112 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14100</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24408</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118788</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853995</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853995</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19400</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14100)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19400)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 552:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The garlande of godly flowers bewtifully adorned as most freshly they flourish in the gardeins of right faithfull Christian writers. Yéeldyng foorth a very comfortable sauour to the afflicted soule, wherby hée is salfly [sic] transported vnto the mercifull throne of the most glorious God. Carefully collected, and diligently digested into ordre, by Tho. Twyne, Gentleman. 1574.</title>
                  <author>Twyne, Thomas, 1543-1613.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[140] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By William How,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1574]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ [par.]⁴ B-Q⁴ R² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19400:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19400:1"/>
            <p>¶ The Garlande of Godly Flowers, Bewtifully adorned as moſt freſhly they flouriſh in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deins of right faithfull Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian writers. Yéeldyng foorth a very comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſauour to the afflicted Soule, wherby hée is ſalf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tranſported vnto the mercifull throne of the moſt glorious God.</p>
            <p>Carefully collected, and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently digeſted into ordre, by Tho. Twyne, Gentleman. 1574.</p>
            <q>
               <p>I will take it on my ſhoulder, and as a Garland binde it about my head.</p>
               <bibl>Iob. 11.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London, by William How.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:19400:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19400:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19400:3"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <q>MEDIOCRIA FIRMA.</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19400:3"/>
            <head>To the Right hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſyr Nicholas Bacon Knight, one of the Queenes Maieſties moſt honourable priuie Counſell, and Lorde kéeper of the great ſeale of England. And to the Right honorable and moſt verte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Ladie, <hi>Anne,</hi> his wife, my very good Lorde and Mayſter: Ladie and Mayſtreſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>ALKING</hi> in this vale of Miſerie, chec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with the choa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge cares of this mortall life, mated with the manifolde calamities whereunto the whole po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steritie of our firſt Father <hi>Adam</hi> is ſubiect: <hi>I</hi> finde nothing (right honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable my good Lorde, and Lady) wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb facs="tcp:19400:4"/>the hart of man can take more quiet and caſt foorth a ſurer anker of ſtabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie to ride ſalfe from the vncertaine ſurges of this wicked worlde, or enter into a calmer Hauen: then into the vndoubted harbour, and comfortable porte of Praier. Heerein, although wee bee neuer ſo mutche toſſed with troubles, weeried with vexations, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted with afflictions, pinched with paines, oppreſſed with miſeries, girded with greifes, and ſlayne with perſecutions: yet wee may finde aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red releife, certaine ſuccour, conſtant comfort, and ſpeedie deliuerance. And no meruell. For although it ſumtimes ſo vnhappely fall out, that eeuen the moſt expert and wiſeſt Mariners, when they haue attayned the Rode after boyſterous ſtormes on th' open ſea, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng themſelues then paſt all daunger, are notwithſtanding caſt a way in the Hauen: yet in the midſt of our miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and very depth of our daungers,
<pb facs="tcp:19400:4"/>if wee turne aboute the helme of our contemplations, and arriue once with in this Rode: wee neede to feare no foule weather, wee weigh no Shippewracke, wee dreade no drowninge. The flittinge of our barke, may aptly repreſent our diſtracted conſcience: the Cable thereof, our Faith, the Anker, frute of good woorkes faſt linked to the ſame: the Ankeradge, is Chriſte our ſauiour: on whom if our cable do ſtrike, and our Anker take holde: the grounde neuer fayleth vs, for it is a firme rocke, it yeeldeth not at the rage of winde nor weather, for it is not ſetled vpon the ſand. In ſutch like ſort, it pleaſed ſumtime our ſweet Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, the diuine wiſdom of God the fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, by groſſe and baſe terme to figure himſelf, the better to bee conceaued by our blinded vnderſtanding, that know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yng the nature and diſpoſition of the thing: wee might likewiſe in all our troubles and afflictions stay, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:19400:5"/>and our praier to bee effectuall. Then ſhal wee feele immediatly a woonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful operation of the holy ghoſt within our hartes, aſſuryng vs of the greate, and tendre mercie of God towards vs, wherin wee are eftſoones emboldned to crie vnto him, <hi>Abba father,</hi> thy wil bee doone in earth as it is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. This is the meanes whereby the auntient heroicall perſonages of the olde teſtament beecame, as it were, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar with God. For by this hee was felt in a combat of wreſtlyng al night ſeene in the burnyng buſshe, heard in a calme after a windie tempeſt, and dayly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muned withall in the mount. By faithfull praier, God preſerueth the righteous in the true way, bringeth backe ſutche as goe aſtray, ſtayeth vp thoſe that ſtande, helpeth vp ſutche as fall, comforteth the weake conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, lighteneth the ſorowfull hart, chee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the heauie, refreſsheth the laden, erecteth the afflicted from the deepe
<pb facs="tcp:19400:5"/>dungeon of blacke deſperation, and crowneth him with immortallitie.</p>
            <p>I neede not in this place to call now to recorde the priuie experimentes, &amp; triall herein of many other men, ſince that <hi>I</hi> my poore ſelf, for the ſhort time that God hath led foorth my daies in this life, haue moſt ſharpely taſted the ſower of th' one, and moſt comfortably tried the ſweete of the other. Not that <hi>I</hi> haue bin a great eye ſore vnto Fortune, as wee daily ſee there bee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe, as by her greeuouſly enuied at, aſſaulted, beaten, caſt downe, troden, ſpurned, driuen to duſt, conſumed to no thing, for <hi>I</hi> neuer poſſeſſed the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of any ſutch ſtorming caſualities. Yet in my ſlendre Boate hath shee ſhip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ped her bitter Oare, ſhee hath blowne a contrarie gale in my hoyſed ſaile, ſhee hath ſouſed my Suger with Salt, and ſeaſoned my ſweete Syrup with vnpleaſant <hi>Aloes,</hi> ſhee hath frow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vpon my felicitie, and doone hir
<pb facs="tcp:19400:6"/>beſt to bring mee to nought, and now ſhee triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pheth for the victorie, wher to <hi>I</hi> muſt of force haue yeelded, had <hi>I</hi> not ſuſtained my ſelfe only with this moſt worthy benefite, wherby <hi>I</hi> haue bin ſufficiently inſtructed how to eſtee me the frownings, or fawnings of this wicked world. As for the vſe of Praier it is expedient in our youth: and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie in our olde age. By this the poore wretches doo tollerate their neede, and the ritche obtaine power to enioy their wealth. Both the prince and the ſubiect, whatſoeuer bee the puiſance of the one, or the condicion of the other: haue continuall neede of recourſe vnto praier, wherby they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come humble ſueters to th'omnipotent God in reſpect of their imperfections and vnrighteouſneſſe, wherin he hath included the ſunnes of men as witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> ſaying: <hi>If wee ſay that wee haue no ſinne: wee deceaue our ſelues, and there is no trueth in vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19400:6"/> And <hi>Iob</hi> likewiſe ſpeaketh of all men in his owne perſon: <hi>If I will iuſtefie my ſelfe, mine owne mouthe ſhall condemne mee: If I will bee a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect man, God ſhall prooue mee a wicked doer:</hi> and alſo in another place, he fitly layth foorth the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of our nature, where hee ſaith: <hi>Man that is borne of a woman hath but a ſhort date of life, and is reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with many miſeries.</hi> The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete aſſaultes whereof, when they ſhall, as dayly they doo, with remorſe of conſcience, withdraw your honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable perſonages a while from th' ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomable conuerſation in ordinarie affayres, priuatly to profeſſe your guilt, and hartely to humble your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues beefore the maieſtie of God, with feruent affection in lowly praier: if you ſhall take into your handes this litle booke, which I haue termed a <hi>Garland,</hi> eftſoones ſelecting ſome one or two
<hi>Flowers</hi> therein contained, as
<pb facs="tcp:19400:7"/>occaſion ſhall ſerue from your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founder meditations: <hi>I</hi> doo not diſtruſt, but that haply your honours may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue ſum ſutche ſooteneſſe of ſauour therin, as ſhall not offend your ſenſe, mutchleſſe the maieſtie of God, as to the good liking of the one, and the glory of the other: <hi>I</hi> haue bin ſo bold to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy the ſmall trauaile of gathering theſe few Flowers into order of your honourable names, and to offre them vnto you, knitting them vp in one
<hi>Garland,</hi> expreſsing therby, as was mine endeuor, the abſolute circle of commendable Graces and Vertues, apparant to the world, iointly couched in your Right honourable perſons.</p>
            <p>A most certain preſident wherof may bee, the one of you by our moſt prudent Prince, doubtleſſe at the ſecret motion of <hi>GOD,</hi> rayſed vnto ſutch highneſſe in Honour as match with the beſt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour to none: <hi>I</hi> neede ſeeke for no farther occaſions of commendation, or
<pb facs="tcp:19400:7"/>auntient titles of worship or honour, the ſiluered heares giuing euident to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the golden wit, and the honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable age<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of the verteous forepaſſed life, and the many yeres of the bleſsing of the moſt higheſt God. On th' other ſide bewtified with a louing Lady, the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpringe of an excellent race, Nice to rightwoorship full Grandſiers, daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to a woorthy Knight, Schollar to a learned ſcholemaiſter, Siſter to a right honourable Lady, Moother of mutch hoped impes, Aunt to a peereleſſe cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe, Wife to a noble Counſeller, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of a Godly Famely, Subiect to a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge Prince, a trewe woorſhipper of Almightie God. Vnto whoſe good pleaſure, for the prolonging and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of both your liues in increſe of godlie Honour, and all other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightes apperteininge, whereby the race of this tranſitorie life may bee made leſſe irkſome to the bodie, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudiciall to the ſoule: <hi>I</hi> am bownden
<pb facs="tcp:19400:8"/>dayly to pray, the effect whereof hee graunte, who tendreth our iuſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtes, and is the only giuer of all goodneſſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>At London
<date>this firſt day of Ianuarie. 1574.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your honours euer at com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundment. <hi>T. Twine.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <q>FATIS VOLENTIBVS.</q>
                  <q>VIRTVTE DVCE.</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:19400:8"/>
            <lg type="acrostic">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>N</hi>o worldly pelfe, ſee thee from God do call.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi>ncline thine hart to doo the thyng is iuſt.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>C</hi>onfirme thy Faith that thou doo neuer fall.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>H</hi>olde faſt on GOD, in him repoſe thy truſt.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O</hi>bſerue thy wayes, amende what is a miſſe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>L</hi>ay vp thy wealth where ruſt may do no harme.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A</hi>mende thy crimes while vacant time there is.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>S</hi>ubmit thy cauſe vnto Gods mightie arme.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A</hi>uenge thee not when thou canſt well repay,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>N</hi>euer let vices harbour in thine hart.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>N</hi>eedes vrgent law conſider thou alway.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>E</hi>ke to the poore doo of thy goodes impart.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>B</hi>eware of Pride, by Glorie ſet no price.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A</hi>vvay from giltleſſe blood turne backe thy face.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>C</hi>onſider ſutes, weigh cauſes once or twice,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O</hi>pen thy mouth on wydowes wofull caſe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>N</hi>othing from Praier let thee once diſſeuer.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>E</hi>nſue this lore: and thou ſhalt liue for euer.</l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="piece">
            <pb facs="tcp:19400:9"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap> there conſiſteth life and welfare vnto my ſowle, and by breatch and viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nothing elſe but ſeuere ſentence of finall dampnation:</p>
            <p>Therfore I cannot tell, moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable wretch as I am, how I ſhuld preſume to approche thée for mercie, I dare not ſhew my ſelfe beefore thée, but if it were poſſible, I would glad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly hide my ſelf from thy ſight, where thou mighſt not finde mée out, that by ſutch meanes I might eſcape thy dreadfull iudgement.</p>
            <p>Howbeit, O Lorde, thou art the mightie God, to whom all things in heauen and earth are knowne, whoſe eies béeholde what is done in the top of the higheſt, and in the bottome of the deapeſt places in the world.</p>
            <p>In thy ſight Lord, the moſt ſecret thoughtes of the harte are open, and from thée there are no cogitations, pretences, practiſes, deuiſes, nor the ſmalleſt motions of the mind, hidden.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19400:9"/>Vnto thée therefore, with trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blinge and teares I returne, appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from thy high, dread, and terry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble throne of iuſt iudgement, remoo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uing my cauſe to thy moſt ſwéete, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miable, pleaſaunt, and comfortable court of thy manifold mercies.</p>
            <p>Euen there, Lord, thou haſt layde vp ſutch ſtore and abundance of gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, pardons, &amp; forgiuenes of ſinnes: that they do ſurmounte the numbre, and ouerſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>read the greatnes of al thy wonderfull woorkes.</p>
            <p>Héere then it is, O my God, that I dare to appeare béefore thy diuine Maieſtie, a fylthye ſinner béefore a mercifull God, a very lumpe of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes beefore the eternall creator of all thinges, of ineſtimable wiſdome, that takeſt mercie vppon our weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and infirmitie: béecauſe thou wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt well the ſtuffe, and ſubſtaunce wherof thou haſt made vs.</p>
            <p>Béeholde, Lord, I call vnto mée,
<pb facs="tcp:19400:10"/>thy dearelybéeloued ſonne, my moſt louing redéemer and ſauiour Iheſus Chriſte to bée myne aduocate, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto his own fréewil and volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie offering, in whom, and through whom, by his moſt precious bloudde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhed vnto thée, vpon the acceptable al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare of the Croſſe, in liew of the dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble death that wée ſhould al haue died for our-moſt horrible offences:</p>
            <p>Pardon I béeſéech thée, O god, my gréeuous iniquities, forgyue mée all my wickednes, releaſe my necligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, remit mine ignorances, abandon the lothſomenes of my ſinnes, which from my mothers wombe vnto this preſent day, I haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted or ſhall do hereafter vnto my liues ende.</p>
            <p>That béeing ſo clenſed, and purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from all contagion of ſinfull impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie: let mée obtayn a liuely and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent fayth at thy handes, ſtedfaſtly to call vpon thée in moſt hartie prayer.</p>
            <p>Lord, in all my neceſſities, aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities,
<pb facs="tcp:19400:10"/>troubles, and afflictions: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme my harte that I may put my whole truſt and affiance in thy ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ieſtie, and ſéeke none other meanes, nor take none other comfort: but in reading thy worthy woorde, or in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to thée in moſt faithful, and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall ſupplications.</p>
            <p>If at any tyme, Lorde, as is the frailtie of our corruptible nature, and the inceſſant ſuggeſtions of Sathan our auncient enemie, I féele in my ſelfe any faintnes or fayling of fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uencie, in calling continually vppon thée: kindle thou then my hart with the heauenly heate of thy holy ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Graunt mée grace, to crie with thy hollie Apoſtle for encreaſe of faithe, that béeing awaked and ſtirred vppe through thée: I may enioy the effect of my godly deſiers, which thou haſt promiſed to yelde vnto mée, through thy ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, my ſauiour.</p>
            <p>Performe, my God, that whiche
<pb facs="tcp:19400:11"/>thou haſt indented with thy ſelly ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, who with anguiſhe of minde ſéeketh after the comfort of thy face, continue in mée the cuſtome to call vpon thée in praier, and all the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of my body ſhal not ceaſe to ſing thy ſacred praiſe. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="piece">
            <head>J.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>¶ If yee beeing euil, know to giue your children good giftes: how mutch more will your Father which is in heauen, giue good thinges to them that aske them?</q>
            </epigraph>
            <head>¶ The ſecond Flower.</head>
            <p>IN moſt hartie hope of thy many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold mercies, and with lowly reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, O euerlaſting God, loe, thus I draw nighe vnto thée, béeing ſore laden with th'infinite number of my ſinnes, truſting in thy fatherly good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<pb facs="tcp:19400:11"/>and entier loue, which thou bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt vnto mankinde: thou wilte diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge mée of mine vnrighteouſnes, and waſh away al mine infirmities.</p>
            <p>Thy louing kindenes hath ben in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable, which thou haſt borne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mée ſince my ſimple conception in the tender intrailes of my mother, within whoſe body thou dideſt laye forth the platforme of my body, and gaueſt vnto mée the repreſentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a man, thy beſtbéeloued and cumli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt creature.</p>
            <p>After this, in due maturitie of time according to the eſtabliſhed and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie ſeaſon, aſſigned by thy heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſedome: thou broughteſt mée foorth into this worlde, my firſt tune giuyng proofe of the vnhappie condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, that I ſhould enioy therin.</p>
            <p>Lorde, thou knoweſt how that ſo ſoone as I was deliuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wombe: euen then I béegan my life in féeblenes and ſorow, and the <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:19400:12"/>my thoughte, kéepe myne eies from ſeing it, myne eares from hearing it, and my ſenſe of féeling from concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing delight in it.</p>
            <p>But cauſe mée to take a ſingular delectation in all thinges that maye pleaſe thée, put away from mée al er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring from thy waies, all wéerines of thy will, all lothſomnes of thy loue.</p>
            <p>Take from mée all pride and ſelf liking, that I may conceaue no good opinion of my ſelfe for that which is none of myne own, let mée not think I am ritch in thée when I am poore, that I ſée when I am blinde, that I am hid when I am naked, that I am iuſt when I am vnrighteous, that I am ſomthing when I am nothing.</p>
            <p>As for the infinitie of my offences, which in numbre ſurpas the ſandes of the ſea: giue vnto mee a cléere ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of thy heauenlie light, O my god, that I may béehold them, a penitent hart that I may confeſſe them, plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull
<pb facs="tcp:19400:12"/>teares that I may bée waile the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, a wonderfull miſlikinge that I may abhorre them.</p>
            <p>O Lorde, is there any thing that fleſh an Bloud may glorie of in thy ſight? no truely, for thou haſt aſked vs what wée haue which wée haue not receaued? from the fountaine of thy fulnes wée haue drawne all that wée haue enioyed, and of our ſelues there is not one that doth good, no Lord, not one.</p>
            <p>Create in mée therefore, O graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lorde, a new hart, and a new ſoule, confirme mée in thy faith that I may not fall, erect mee in all good woorkes that bée acceptable in thy ſight, then cannot my mouthe ceaſe but alwayes bée ſhewyng thy péere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe praiſes, and milde mercies.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="piece">
            <pb facs="tcp:19400:13"/>
            <head>C.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>¶ Come not in the path of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, and walke not in the way of the wicked. Caſt all your care vpon God, for hee careth for you.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <head>¶ The thirde Flower.</head>
            <p>COme vnto mée all yée that tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell and bée heauie laden, crieſt thou, O my moſt ſwéet ſauiour, and I will refreſh you. Here now I come vnto thée, offryng my ſelfe bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy heauenly maieſtie, lowly fallyng downe vpon the knees of my hart, holdynge vp the handes of my Faith, wherby I may take moſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured hope of thee, and come vnto thée.</p>
            <p>Draw mée vnto thee for els I am not able to come, I can doo nothynge therto of my ſelfe, not ſo mutche as
<pb facs="tcp:19400:13"/>thinke one good thought, mutchleſſe merite or deſerue to preſume vnto thee, vpon reſpect of any mine owne woorthineſſe.</p>
            <p>As for my woorthineſſe, it is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woorthineſſe béefore thée, my though<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes bee ſinfull, my deedes bee dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, and if thou haue reguard vnto my merites: then am I ſure to haue damnation for my deſert, and Hell for mine hier.</p>
            <p>O thou almightie, béefore whom the Angels tremble at their impuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the Sonne is fowle, the Moone is filthy, the Starres vncleane, and the heauens are corrupt: what can I haue to boaſt of, but of mine owne natural vnclenlineſſe, and that I am the childe of perdition?</p>
            <p>Supplie thou my defects, O God, and what is wantyng in mee: make it perfect through thee, which art the ſumme of all goodnes, and perfection vnto the righteous, let mee not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part
<pb facs="tcp:19400:14"/>deſtitute from thee, for in thee is the fulneſſe of felicitie.</p>
            <p>Heere where I am Lorde, I am laden ſore and greeuouſly ouerpreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the burden of my ſinnes, they weigh mee greeuouſly downe to the grounde, I cannot looke vp, and my cruſſhed bones doo ake with extreeme wéerineſſe.</p>
            <p>Come, O Lorde, O come ſpeede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſet to thy helpyng hande, take from mée this wright of wickednes, cleere mée from this clogge of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and ſeuere mee from this ſinke of ſinne.</p>
            <p>Humble my Harte, that I may haue no vayne likyng of my ſelf, and that my freindes, neighbours, and acquaintnance, finally the world fall into no diſpleaſure againſt mée ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, but eſpecially thy maieſtie, for it is a greeuous offence.</p>
            <p>Fortifie my minde with the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt armour of pacience, that I may
<pb facs="tcp:19400:14"/>take in good part all mockes, ſcoffes, reproches, and perſecutions for thy truethes ſake, and when I am proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: let mee bee founde faithfull.</p>
            <p>Confirme mee fully, O my crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, in thy Trueth and al godlineſſe, let no ſhininge of promotions, nor thundre of threatninges, nor windie puffes of wordlie vanitie, pluck mee from that whiche is right, but let thy will bee my way, and thy law my delight.</p>
            <p>Driue away all dimneſſe from mine eyes, and ſluggiſhneſſe from my feete, that I may ſpeedely bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, and diligently fulfill to my a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, the leaſt poynt and iote of thy preceptes, wherto when I haue ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied my ſelfe: yet am I to to mutch an vnprofitable ſeruaunt, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge let thy tendre mercie al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes preuent mee, O my moſte ſweeteſt God.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt lified mee vp aloſt in
<pb facs="tcp:19400:15"/>the ſight of thy people, and haſte in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued mee with greate honour aboue my peeres and equalles, graunt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mee likewiſe ſo mutche to excell them in vertue and godlineſſe, make mée a worthy miniſter and ſteward of thy giftes, conſideryng that all po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and aucthoritie commeth from thee, and that thou raiſeſt the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on high to caſt him downe low, and the loftier his ſeat is: the more great, and gréeuous is his fall.</p>
            <p>Engendre in mée, good Lorde, a greedie deſier to do Iuſtice, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thée alwaies béefore mine eies, and printyng thy iudgements with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in my hart: I may bee free from all affection, and pure from all partiali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, hauyng no reſpect to the perſons, but vprightly weighyng the cauſes, that thereby the trueth may bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunced, and vniuſtice condempned.</p>
            <p>Remooue from mee all corruption in iudgement, and vnrighteouſnes

<pb facs="tcp:19400:15"/>in dealyng, kéepe my mouth from le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinges, and my handes from bloud, remembryng that thou art the ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of the hart and raines, that ſhalt come to iudge the quicke and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead, repaying vnto euery man accordyng vnto the woorks of his owne hands.</p>
            <p>Forgiue mée, O my Lorde, and my God, the wickedneſſe of my fore paſſed life, remembre not mine of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, neither the offences of my prediceſſours to lay them vnto my charge, lay foorth the direct line of thy law béefore my féete, that I may walke therein with out erryng, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate a new will within mée to perſeuere in thy way, holde mee vp therin that I doo not fall, pricke mee foorth that I doo not fainte, and my toongue ſhal talke continually of thy moſte glorious goodnes.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="piece">
            <pb facs="tcp:19400:16"/>
            <head>H.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>¶ Happie are thoſe ſeruants, whom the Lorde when hee commeth, ſhal finde wakyng. Verely I ſay vnto you, that hee ſhall girde himſelf, and make them to ſit downe to meate, and will come foorth, and ministre vnto them.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <head>¶ The fourth Flower.</head>
            <p>HArken vnto the voice of the Lord thy God, O my feely ſoule, and heare what cheerefull promiſes hée hath repoſed in ſtore for thée, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that when ſoeuer thou repenteſt thée of thy ſinnes from the bottome of thy hart: hée will blotte out the remembrance of them for euermore ſo that they ſhall neuer bée imputed vnto thée.</p>
            <p>O come then with ſpéede, and with all ſubmiſſion caſt foorth the intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb facs="tcp:19400:16"/>burden of thy moſte lothſome luſtes béefore the Lorde, call vnto him that hée woulde ſet open the ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of his manifolde mercies vnto thée, giue thée a perfect penitent hart, and the ſpirite of conſtancie to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuere in the ſame.</p>
            <p>Bende downe thine heauely eies, O Lorde, from the celeſtiall throne of thy glorie, and béeholde the ſtate and condition of mée that lie héere in the earth béelow, waltrynge in this vale of wickedneſſe, drenched in this dungeon of darkeneſſe, martired in millians of miſeries, couched in this cloake of calamities, loſte in this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berinth of luſtes, ſmoultred in this ſmoke of ſenſualitie, greatly grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng from grace, and voide of vertue.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, as thou haſte at this preſent time: ſo continew with day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly increaſing in mée, a lothyng of my ſelf in reſpect of ſinne, a deſier vnto thée by meane of faithfull praier,
<pb facs="tcp:19400:17"/>hartie contrition, poſſible ſatiſfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, innouation of life, continuation of Grace, tendynge vnto the preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion both of my body, and ſoule.</p>
            <p>Send downe vnto mée, Lorde, the cleere lookyng glaſſe of thy wiſdoome, that I may béeholde therin th' ougle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomeneſſe and deformitie of mine vnrighteouſnes, giue mée a Viale ful of the water of vnfained repentance, that ſprincklyng my ſelf therwith, although I were with ſinnes more read then ſcarlet: I may bée made more white then ſnow.</p>
            <p>Waſh away the filthineſſe of my ſinnes with a branche of bitter I ſop, wherein is figured the vnpleaſant faſt of afflictions, troubles, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions ſent vnto vs by thy hande, moſt righteous God, in liew of our offences, and I ſhall béecome paſſing pure.</p>
            <p>Neuertheles ouercharge mee not, O ſwéet Lorde, I béeſéeche thée, nor
<pb facs="tcp:19400:17"/>lay not more vpon my backe then I am able to carie, for thou knoweſt beſt th'infirmitie of my fraile fleaſh, and the weakenes of our kinde, ſince wée all bée thine, and the worke of thy holly handes.</p>
            <p>O my God, what is there in this worlde that men ſhould bée ſo gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to continue therin, and ſo lothe to forgoe the fruition of this tranſitorie life? while wée remayne héere wee are all touched with troubles, thoſe that haue wealth at will are checked with calamities, yea Princes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues are not alwayes at eaſe, bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that wée heape vp dayly the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert of thy iudgement.</p>
            <p>Whilſt my dayes bée prolonged within this darke den of mortallitie: lighten the Lantern of thy diuine woord béefore my feete, that I ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble not agaynſt the heape of my hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous offences, and fall downe head long into the déepe Dungeon of deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19400:18"/>Likewiſe, plucke from mée the fonde Feathers of ſaucie preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, leaſt takyng an hautie conceite in my ſelfe to bee that which (alas) I am not: thou reueale my filthineſſe, and caſt mée downe thither where there is no redemption.</p>
            <p>Gratiouſly graunt vnto mee, O my Lorde, and Kynge, that I may neuer take my ſelfe to bée other then in deede I am, make mée to bée ſutch one as I ought, and let mée bée hée that I would, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal I neuer dwell in errour, thy fauour ſhoulde neuer fayle mee, and hereafter (which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandyng I hope) bée an inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritour of thy heauenly kyngdome.</p>
            <p>Lorde, I béeſéeche thée keepe mee that I neuer fall into reprobate ſence and let mée not bée ſeduced by any falſe doctrine, let the lines of thy law bee printed in the bowels of my bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, lighten, inflame, and confirme the hartes of thy choſen people, that they
<pb facs="tcp:19400:18"/>may haue one minde, one will, all a like ſeeke thee, finde thee, ſee thee, and magnifie thy glorious name.</p>
            <p>Preuent all my dooinges with thy moſt fauourable kyndenes, O father of mercies, and ſo direct my wayes in thy Faith, and feare of thy maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie: that I may commit no wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, nor conſent thereto, let there bee founde no guilt in my handes, nor guile in my hart, preſerue my lippes from lies, from incontinencie mine eyes, my fleaſh from filth, my ſowle from ſinne, and the whole courſe of my life from offence, &amp; tranſgreſſion.</p>
            <p>O Lorde, heare my praiers, let myne erneſt crie come into thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and entre into thine Eares, whiche I yeeld heere vnto thee from the very deapth of my Hart, with a wounded conſcience, and a bleedyng ſoule, with broken ſighes, and wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng eyes, bended knees, and ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched handes, but which moſt is: with
<pb facs="tcp:19400:19"/>ardent affection, and feruent Faith.</p>
            <p>Bende downe thy ſelfe, O bende downe vnto my piteous playntes, thou God of our Fathers, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng as thou haſt ſpoken: let it ſo bée doone vnto thy ſeruant. Great is thy grace: O graunt mée thy grace, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifolde are thy mercies: O ſhew mée thy mercie, puiſant is thy power: O ſende mee thy power, that I may turne from ſinne and turne to thee, leaue my olde life and leade a new, that I may alwaies bee thy ſeruant, and thou likewiſe eternally bée mine eternall God.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="piece">
            <head>O.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>¶ O thou Earth, Earth, Earth, heare the woorde of the Lorde. Of a trueth <hi>GOD</hi> hath no reguarde of perſons, but in euery nation, hee that feareth him, and woorketh righteouſneſſe: is accepted with him.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <pb facs="tcp:19400:19"/>
            <head>¶ The fift Flower.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> Euerlaſtyng <hi>GOD,</hi> and moſte louyng Father, maker of all the world, kyng of Bliſſe, Lorde of Life, giuer of peace, and continuer of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde, looke downe into the bottome and deapth of my conſcience, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the perpetuall afflictions which dayly I ſuſtayne therin, to the daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous diſtreſſe, &amp; wonderful woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Strengthen mee, O Lord, againſt the furious inuaſions of three my moſte mortall foes, the Fleaſh, the Worlde, and the Deuill, whiche to th'intent they might ſuppreſſe mee: ceaſe not continually withall theyr force, to aſſayle the ſéely ſpirite which thou haſt lent vnto mee, the woorke of thy wiſedome, and the image of thy ſubſtance.</p>
            <p>My moſte ſweet God, keepe mee
<pb facs="tcp:19400:20"/>with the winges of thy vertue, aſiſt mee with thy holy ghoſt, that I may heedfully withholde my feete from all ſnares, and trappes, whiche may any way intangle mee, &amp; withdraw mee from due obedience towardes thee and thy will, ſtaying mee from walkyng forwarde in thy heauenly heaſtes that lead to life.</p>
            <p>For Satan myne auntient ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, ſeeketh out a thouſand meanes to beguile mee, hée excelleth in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teltie, hée aboundeth in craftes, hee paſſeth in wilineſſe, in ſo mutch that hee tranſformeth his lothſome ſhape into the likeneſſe of an Angell of light, therby to ſupplant thine elect, but defende thou mee from him, O my moſt mightie God.</p>
            <p>Pondre the nature and diſpoſition of my frayle fleaſh, how it is nothing els but the graue of my ghoſt, a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thell of infirmities, a lumpe of lothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomneſſe, a priſon of perdition, a ſink
<pb facs="tcp:19400:20"/>of ſinne, and a frame of frowarde moulde, contrarie to that whiche is good, and alwaies promptly preſt to the worſe.</p>
            <p>As for this worlde: it is the vale of wilfulneſſe, the way of wicked co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, a iorney fraught with io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perdie, a pilgrimage fully pight with pitious pininges, a deepe dungeon of deſtruction, an infectious ſoyle with ſinfulneſſe, a lake of vnlawful luſtes and a tree of traiterous fruites, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant, O God, to thy moſte ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred will.</p>
            <p>The Deuill is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> déerlyng of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, the Prince of dreadful darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the Kynge of calamities, the wicked woorker of woes, the Fende of finall deſtruction, the greedie ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for mans procured perdition, the poyſoned puddle of lies, the ſneaking Snake of ſinne, the ſerpent of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome temptations, the minger of all miſcheifes, and the ouerthrower
<pb facs="tcp:19400:21"/>of vertues.</p>
            <p>But, O thou moſt glorious God, as thou haſt lightned my vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng and perſeuerance in theſe, to diſcerne what is hurtfull to mee, and diſpleaſant to thee: diſpoſe euen ſo the hart of thy ſeruant with the day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly influence of thy grace, that I may bée acquit from al ſuch ſharpe aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes as may winne mée from thee, but confirme mée in all Godlineſſe, trueth, and faithfulneſſe.</p>
            <p>Make my harte the vndefiled in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of pure, &amp; perfect thoughts, and my tungue the Trump of thine eternall prayſe, my bodie the habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the holly Ghoſt, myne eyes the windowes to beholde the worthy way that leadeth vnto thée, my leg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges the ſupporters of my bodie and ſoule, towardes th'attainment of thy heauenly kyngdome.</p>
            <p>Incline mine eares, that I may giue diligent attendance vnto thy
<pb facs="tcp:19400:21"/>moſte bleſſed will, and commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, expreſſed in thy moſte ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred woorde, mollifie the hardneſſe of my hart that it may eaſely entre in, and firmely take roote, to th'increaſe of ſemblant ſeedes of vertu and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe in mee, graunt this, O Lorde for my delight is in thy ſeruice.</p>
            <p>Knocke harde, O Lorde God, O knocke harde at the doore of my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, with the ringle of thy moſte holly wil, awake mée out of the ſnor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng ſleepe of ſecuritie in ſinnynge, whereout manie doo neuer riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne but vtterly periſh, put mee in minde of my duetie towardes thy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine maieſtie, let mée haue the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to know my ſelf, and that thou only art my good Lorde and God.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe with gréeuous gronyng of hart, that I haue manifoldly tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed thy commaundementes, in ſeekyng thee I haue embraced that which I ſhould haue refuſed, I haue
<pb facs="tcp:19400:22"/>ſtragled longe whilſt I ſhould haue walked in thy wayes, and trode in thy pathes, I haue gone backe when I ſhould haue purſued thy pleaſure, and haue trained my ſelfe in the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe of thy teachynges.</p>
            <p>Leade mée, O Lorde, with thy heauenly hande and I ſhalbée truely lead, dirext mee with the ſpirite of vnderſtandyng and I ſhalbée ſaulfly directed, let y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bright burnyng lampe of thy woonderfull woorde ſtill ſhyne béefore mine eyes, and pearce into my harte, ſo ſhall I bée ſure not to treade one ſteppe amiſſe, bée thou al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes my moſt mercifull God, and make mée continually thy moſt obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient childe.</p>
            <p>Blot the beadroule of my miſdee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des out of thy remembrance, O thou kynge of mercie, and indorſe the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordes of my tranſgreſſions with a diſcharge of thy great compaſſion, ſet thy holly hande vpon my harte in to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb facs="tcp:19400:22"/>that I am thy childe, and write the woordes of thy pleaſure in my breaſt, make mée aſſured that I am one whom thou haſte predeſtinated vnto life.</p>
            <p>Glorifie thy ſelf in mée, Lorde, for I am thy woork, and let mée bee glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified in thée, for thou art my <hi>GOD,</hi> my ſtrength, my ſaluation, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, purifie my ſoule that thou mayſt dwell in mée, and graunt I may bée made woorthy to dwell in thee, for thou art in althinges, and althinges are in thée, to thée therfore bée praiſe and honour for euer and euer.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="piece">
            <head>L.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>¶ Learne to do wel, applie your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to equatie, deliuer the oppreſſed, helpe the Fatherleſſe to his right, let the widdowes complaint come before you.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <pb facs="tcp:19400:23"/>
            <head>¶ The ſixt Flower.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>LORDE,</hi> in thy moſte louynge mercies, haue I alwayes put my whole truſt and confidence, wherfore thou haſte aſſured mée that I ſhall come to no reproche nor ſhame, there ſhal no ignominie nor confuſion take holde vpon mee, and although there ſhould riſe whole thouſandes of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked conſpiratours againſt mée: yet ſhould they not preuayle, for thou art the portion of my hope.</p>
            <p>Accordynge vnto whiche moſte ſwéeteſt couenantes of thine: ſo let thy kindeneſſe more then fatherlie compaſſe mée alwayes, like the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wherwith I am couered, let thy mercies bée vnto mée a ſhielde of defence, and a buckler of aſſured pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, that I may neuer dread the furie of any foe, ſtriue hée to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw my bodie or ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19400:23"/>O turne the hartes of thoſe that hate mée without a cauſe, or bée offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with mée for thy bleſſinges ſake wherewith thou haſt bleſſed mée, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becauſe thou haſt increaſed mee with wealth, or aduaunced mée to honour, or lifted mée into the fauour of my gracious Soueraigne, wherin I yéelde thy maieſtie moſte hartie thankes.</p>
            <p>Make mée, O Lorde, a méete me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber for the vocation whervnto thou haſt called mée, graunt mee the gifte of godlineſſe: as thou haſte planted mee in prehemine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of place, let ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue flowriſh and vice bée ſuppreſſed, the righteous cauſe of the Orphane, widowe, and ſutche as are deſtitute preuayle, and the oppreſſour receaue his deſerued foyle.</p>
            <p>Bryng it thou to effect, O almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God, from whom procéedeth the motion of all good thoughtes, that as thou haſt made thine onely Sonne,
<pb facs="tcp:19400:24"/>our Sauiour Chriſte, the ſole ſheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of thy faithfull flocke: ſo wee may all know his voyce, and follow him in ſinceritie of life, and puritie of doctrine, all the dayes of our life.</p>
            <p>I hartly béeſéeche thee, Lorde, that in conſideration of mine vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe: thou giue mee not ouer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the handes of mine enemies, and ſutch as fayne woulde ſee my fal, and reioyce at my finall deſtruction, and eſpecially deliuer mée from falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, and preachers, whiche ſeeke only their owne commoditie, and not the edefication of thy hungrie peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſoules.</p>
            <p>Cauſe mee to take a moſte ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lare delight in the readynge, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng of thy holly Goſpell, to frame my life accordyng vnto the ſacred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of thy woorthie woorde, without whiche: all other doctrine concernyng the woorſhipping of thée, is deuiliſh and vngodly, and that by
<pb facs="tcp:19400:24"/>all meanes I may ſeeke the ſettyng foorth of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Let the enemies of thy trueth bee enemies vnto mée, that embraſinge their perſons with laudable charitie: I may perſecute their offences vnto th'amendement of their liues and conuerſation, and that they may vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand at length, that thou art a ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous God, and wilt not giue thine honour to another.</p>
            <p>O moſte mightie kynge, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of all gracious goodneſſe, conuert the hartes of all ſutche as perſecute thy Chriſte in his membres thine elect, open their eies I béeſéeche thée that they may béehold their errours, and repent them of their miſdeedes, and confirme the hartes of the afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that they may perſiſt in confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thy name.</p>
            <p>Mercifully cal mée backe, for I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that for my parte I haue walked wronge, thou haſt giuen me
<pb facs="tcp:19400:25"/>vnderſtandynge to perceaue myne owne imperfections, the multitude of them lieth heaped béefore myne eyes, and my harte is ſore gréeued therwith, O comfort mée, good Lord, and quicken mée oftſoonesin thée.</p>
            <p>I haue bin continually more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to offende thy maieſtie, then to execute thy heauenly will, there is no maner of meanes wherin a man may diſpleaſe thée that I am guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, take mercie vpon mée and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue mée therefore, for I am deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined neuer agayne to commit the like, ſtrengthen mee with thy ſpirite that I neuer ſinne hereafter.</p>
            <p>Moſt louynge Father, and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full God, I hartely require thee, for my Lorde Ieſus Chriſtes ſake, graunt mée that I may couet with a prudent minde thoſe thinges that be pleaſant and acceptable vnto thée, that I may finde them eaſely, ſearche them wiſely, know them truely, and
<pb facs="tcp:19400:25"/>exerciſe them effectually, to the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy praiſe of thy glorious name.</p>
            <p>Diſpoſe the whole courſe of my life in ſutche order, that it may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh that whiche thy godly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure requireth at my handes, that I may perfectly know it, haue a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng minde to do it, and power from thée to fulfill it, whereby I may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne thoſe thinges, that bée moſte conuenient for my neceſſities, and appertaynyng to my ſaluation.</p>
            <p>Chéere vp my hart, O my moſte déere God, with the hope of thy plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous promiſes, and make mée al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes as merie as it béecommeth a Chriſtian, and one that feareth God, giue mée grace euer to reioyce in thée and thy godly will, and that I may bée ſorie for nothynge: but onely in dooyng thoſe thinges that draw mee away from thee, to éeuell.</p>
            <p>O Lorde God of infinite wiſdom, inſpire my hart, and direct my voyce
<pb facs="tcp:19400:26"/>that I may not thinke, nor vtter any thinge béefore thée: then that whiche thou knoweſt to bée expedient for mée to aſke, and glorious for thée to giue, turne not my prayer into per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, nor my ſute into ſinne, for thou art my God, on whom I wholy depende, ſaue mée for thy mercies ſake, O ſaue mée, accordynge as I haue alwayes repoaſed my confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in thée.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="piece">
            <head>A.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>¶ A mans almes is as a purſe with him, and ſhall keepe a mans fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour as the apple of an eye: and afterwarde shall it ariſe, and pay euery man his rewarde vpon his head.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <head>¶ The ſeuenth Flower.</head>
            <p>ACcordyng vnto the incomprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible numbre of thy manifolde
<pb facs="tcp:19400:26"/>mercies, O Lorde, take pitie and compaſſion vpon mée, diſcharge mee of the importable fraught of mine in firmities, for thou art hee that loſeſt and none can binde, and that bindeſt and none can loſe, loſe mée therefore I béeſéeche thee, from the lotheſome burden of my ſinne, and binde mee that I may not depart from thy ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes.</p>
            <p>O thou God of my power, make my hart to reſemble the drieſt towe, and let the moſt feruent loue of thy lawes, kindle, as it were, a flaminge fier within my breaſt, that I may ſo bée conſumed with a greedie zeale in fulfillyng thy heaſtes, let no coale of conſcience in aniwiſe extinguiſh this burnyng: nor yet likewarmeneſſe aſwage this heate.</p>
            <p>Let others ſée this in mée, that they may take example thereat and bee confirmed in Godlineſſe, for I am priuily greeued that I haue bin vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acquayne<gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:19400:27"/>deth in dread of thy driry iudgement lookyng for deliuerance, and running for refuge to the redoubted rampier of thy milde mercies.</p>
            <p>Pardon mée, Lorde, if at any time I haue ſought the ayde of any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, neclecting thée that art the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of all thynges, without whom there is no health nor ſaluation, if I haue drunken of the lothſome lakes, and refuſed thee that art the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne of Life, if I haue fully fead on wicked weedes, and paſſed by the holſome herbes of diuine doctrine.</p>
            <p>I haue erred, Lorde, and gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray like a wilfull ſhéepe, and hark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto the voyce of fayned ſheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards that had no part with thée, I haue bin loſte in the wilderneſſe of wicked ſuperſtition and Idolatrie, and torne in the briars of ſutche as ſought my fleece and cared not for my ſoule but to deſtroy it, I haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted of the deadly dewe, and the rotte
<pb facs="tcp:19400:27"/>is entred into my veynes.</p>
            <p>I am extreame ſicke that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand vpon my legges, I am not able to lift vp my voyce for my lun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues are infected, my threat is horce with criyng, I am vexed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a cough, and the terrible ſtitche aſſaulteth me ſo ſore within my ribbes: that I am nothynge but a carcas fraught with care, and a wretche wrapped in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſickeneſſes.</p>
            <p>O come, thou God of my ſaluation come viſite thy poore ſeruant, bring mée home whiche am loſt, and direct mee that haue gone aſtray, teache mée to know the liuely ſounde of thy moſte holly woord, that I may who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly harken therto, and to the voyce of none other that ſhall happen to call vnto mee, ſaying: lo héere is Chriſt, or there is Chriſte.</p>
            <p>Saue mée, Lorde, from the vnſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie ſmell of pharaſaicall ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that my hart neuer bee defiled
<pb facs="tcp:19400:28"/>therewith, and for thy mercie ſake: aſiſt mée moſte graciouſly that I fall not into any dotage of deuiliſh Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie, for thou art a ielous God, and wilt not ſuffer thine honour to bee giuen to other, and béeſides thee ther is none that can helpe.</p>
            <p>I haue fead, O Lorde, to mutche at full vpon the ſugred delightes of this wicked worlde, whiche indeede are ſauced with moſt bitter woorme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, the taſte of them is pleaſant: but the tayle is abhominable tarte, I haue chawed them with pleaſure: but they haue choked mee with ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, they ſeemed vnto mee as toothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Triacles: but I haue founde them peſtilent poyſons.</p>
            <p>Deliuer mee, gratious <hi>GOD,</hi> through thy great goodneſſe, ſay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mee I wilbée thy comfort, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my ſoule I will bée thy phiſition, then ſhall there no daunger daunt my hart, nor ghoſtly greife procure
<pb facs="tcp:19400:28"/>myne anoy, but that I may alwaies cheerefully ſinge foorthe thy noble prayſe for euer.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="piece">
            <head>S.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>¶ Say not vnto thy neighbour, goe thy way and come agayne, tomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row I will giue thee, wheras thou haſt now to giue him.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <head>¶ The eight Flower.</head>
            <p>SAluation, immortalitie, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable pleaſures, O God, are prepared bountifully to embrace thoſe that put their truſt in thee, and without all doubleneſſe of harte, or contagion of ſinne: leade foorthe the lingrynge ſteppes of their lothſome life, in the wayes of trueth and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience towardes thy commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19400:29"/>Thy wayes, moſt ſwéete Lorde, are the wayes of wealthe, and thy commaundementes conducte vnto heauenly honour, thou haſte layde foorth a ſtreigth pathe vnto thoſe that haue grace to walke therin, and thou haſt promiſed moſt ſingular rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, vnto ſutche as obey thy moſte woorthy will.</p>
            <p>As for thy wil: it is the welſpring of welfare, the pathe of peace, the ſea of ſecuritie, the porte of perfection, and the fountayne of all felicitie.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, I would fayne bée clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that I might tread foorthe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of this daungerous pilgrimage, in accompliſhing thy heauenly heaſtes, and fulfilling thy ſtatutes full of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation.</p>
            <p>O thou, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> art the God of al trueth, whiche in puritie doeſt paſſe the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and exceedeſt the ſaincts in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, in reſpect of whoſe hollineſſe: all thinges are vile and ſinfull, my
<pb facs="tcp:19400:29"/>poore pantyng ghoſt ſore longeth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thée, for that thou art the conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of all goodneſſe, &amp; in the ſight of thy glorie: I am aſhamed of mine owne vnrighteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>Lorde, faine would I intreate thy maieſtie, and I doo moſte hartely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt the ſame, that thou wouldeſt béeholde the wofull afflictions, greifs miſeries, ſtripes, ſores, and wounds, which my ſoule ſuſtayneth through the continuall ſurpriſe of my cancred ſinnes, and in the large abundance of thy milde mercies: heale them with thy holly hande.</p>
            <p>Woe am I, my God, that I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peere béefore thée thus couered qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght in a ſacke of ſinne, my filthineſſe maketh mée ſtande in feare of thee, and horrour of my ſelf, I tremble to thinke what one thou ſeeſt of mee, if poſſible thou mayeſt ſée mée for the numbre of my ſinnes that exceede the flowers of the ſpringe, or leaues <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:19400:30"/>thy fatherlie pitie, and forgiueneſſe.</p>
            <p>Turne not away from mée, poore wretch, thy woonted benignitie, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmutch as I confeſſe my daily ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, and although my ſinnes bée mo in number then is for mée méete and ſittinge: yet let thy mercie bée no leſſe then it is decent for ſo gentle and pitieful a god, O god the god of al fauourablenes.</p>
            <p>How mutch the more abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble my ſinnes are in thy ſight, yéel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge foorth a lothſome ſmell of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure in thy preſence O god: ſo mutch the more do they ſtand in néed of holſome cure, which of neceſſitie procéedeth from thée and none other, to requite the ſame with ſutche inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie and newneſſe of life: as may bée acceptable vnto thee.</p>
            <p>Heale therefore, O moſt ſingular good Lorde, my gréeuous infirmitie, and ſo ſhalt thou ridde mée of that whiche offendeth thée my wofull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie,
<pb facs="tcp:19400:30"/>acquite mee from my con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tagious ſickeneſſe: and thou ſhalt ſmel no more my moſt horrible loth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomneſſe, pardon within mée this bit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter calamitie: and nothyng ſhall len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger offende thy ſinceritie.</p>
            <p>Create in mée, O Lorde God, a moſte godly zeale, and feruent deſier to perſeuere alwayes within the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of thy heauenly will, and neuer to commit any thynge that is repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant vnto the ſame, aſiſtyng mée al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo with thy holly ſpirite, that I fayle not in this moſt godly purpoſe, but ſtedfaſtly purſue it vnto the laſt day of my life, ſo ſhall I bée aſſuredly ſalf from ſinne and my toongue ſhall alwayes bée tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge thy pereleſſe prayſes.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="piece">
            <pb facs="tcp:19400:31"/>
            <head>A.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>¶ A gratious woman getteth ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, an huſwifely woman is a crowne vnto her huſband: but shee that beehaueth her ſelf vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſtly, is a corruption in his bones.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <head>¶ The ninthe Flower.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S a childe that hath</hi> tranſgreſſed the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of his maſter, ſtandeth in awe of the rodde: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo, O lorde, am I in greate dread of thy iudgement, for that is the hier of ſutch as obſerue not thy heaſtes, bicauſe I haue not walked after thy will, nor harckned vnto the voyce of thy woorde, but run foorthe on the reigne of myne owne ſenſualitie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19400:31"/>But thou haſte made a couenant with mée, that when ſo euer I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert myſelfe vnto thée: thou wylte fauourably turne thy ſelfe vnto mée, and if I repent: thou wilt forgiue, if I bée ſorie: thou wilt reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber myne offences no longer, ſée then, Lorde, for I bring with mée now the branch of ſorow, and héere I hold it vp vnto thée for a monument of thy remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce.</p>
            <p>Saue mée, good Lorde, as hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thou haſt done, deliuer mée in the day of diſtreſſe, for thou art the horne of my health, and the ſheild of my ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and the gaine of my glorie, I haue no power at all but it procée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from thée, and thou beareſt vp the féeblenes of myne infirmitie, and thy mercie is my ſtaffe to leane vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>From the daungers of death, and from the ſnares of Sathan, and from the cheines of Hell, and when I was ſwallowed vp: thou didſt deliuer my
<pb facs="tcp:19400:32"/>ſoule from deſtruction, I was wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in woe but I am ſet at libertie, as a bird that was fallen into the fow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lers lyme, and at length is loſed by ſome good bodie.</p>
            <p>For theſe thy bountiful benefites, O god, take from mée the vice of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulnes that I may thinke and thanke thée therefore, and graciouſly diſpoſe the waies of thy ſeruant, that I may continew in thy pleaſure, but if thou wouldeſt ſo direct mée that I might offende thée no more: there ſhoulde no ioy bée comparable vnto myne.</p>
            <p>They are hated of thée that do turn thy plentifull bleſſings into ſcarcitie, and they are partakers of their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes that are in aucthoritie ſeinge it, and do not redreſſe it, open their eies, ſwéet god, that they may ſée it, &amp; endeuour their hartes to amend it, that thy people periſhe not throughe the iniquitie of a fewe, that haue hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
<pb facs="tcp:19400:32"/>vp a great ſinne.</p>
            <p>I haue praid vnto thée with an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt hart for all my imperfections, to bée deliuered of them, and nowe I humbly ſue, good Lorde, that thou wouldeſt vouchſalfe to preſerue mée from the déede that may prouoke the bitternes of any mans ſoule againſt mée, for I am aſſured that thou wilt repay it with vengeance.</p>
            <p>There bée ſome that haue laid wait to intrap mée, and they would bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céeding glad of my fall, but my truſt is in thée, that thou wilt not giue mée ouer as a praye to myne ennemies, make their deſiers void, let them bée confounded in their owne drifts, and faile of their purpoſe that they wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly haue inuented.</p>
            <p>Pardon mée, O god, in all my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions, forgiue them that perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute mee, make mée loue them that hate me, and hartely to pray for them that wiſh my finall deſtruction, how
<pb facs="tcp:19400:33"/>beeit, I béeſéech thée, Lorde, to ſaue me from their handes, leſt if thou ſhouldſt forſake mee: I fall into their power, and there bée none to defende mée from their malice.</p>
            <p>Truly, Lord, I am fully determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to make thy precepts a gardeyne of pleaſure, and thy lawes an alley of delight to take my recreation therin during the dayes of my fleſh, only I requeſt thée of thy goodnes to graunt mee thy grace, with the continuance of this good woorke which thou haſt béegun in mee.</p>
            <p>Since thou lotheſt, Lorde, an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly life: giue mee power, I praye thee, to flie the woorkes of the fleſhe which thou doſt hate, and to embrace the deedes of righteouſenes whiche thou doeſt loue, and in them to ſeeke thy glorie, incline my mind alwaies to meditate on thy lawe, and to caſte all the cares of my hart vpon thee.</p>
            <p>The death and buriall, the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
<pb facs="tcp:19400:33"/>&amp; aſcention of thee, my ſwéet ſauiour Chriſte, I humbly adore, and giue hartie thankes for them, for in them there riſeth vnto mee a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of life, through the quickenyng ſmell of all theſe: raiſe vp my ſoule, I pray thée, good Lorde, from the dreadfull death of ſinne.</p>
            <p>O duſt and aſhes, why doeſt thou walke with a proude hart, and ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out neck, and why art thou moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with impacience agaynſt euerie triflynge aduerſitie? Béeholde the méekeneſſe and humilitie of thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déemer, and learne to bee humble of harte, and low of courage, bée aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of pride, and bluſh for want of patience.</p>
            <p>Lorde, if I coulde giue vnto thée Heauen and Earth, and all the glory thereof for hier, from the toppe of my rewarde: I coulde not ſufficiently recompence the deapth of thy deſert, yet giue mée that grace, that ſo farre
<pb facs="tcp:19400:34"/>as mine abilitie extendeth: I may requite thy bountie with thankes, and ſhew how mutch I am bettered by thy heauenly liberalitie.</p>
            <p>Giue mée thy peace whiche the worlde cannot giue, graunt mée the ioy whiche thine elect doo poſſeſſe, ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne mée with the comfort that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhalbée voyde, erect mée with hope that ſhall alwayes perſiſt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct mée with thy woorde that euer ſhall endure, aduaunce mee to thy kyngdome that neuer ſhall ende, and thy glorie ſhall ſtill liue in mée, for I ſhall neuer die.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="piece">
            <head>N.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>¶ No thought may eſcape God, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may any woord bee hid from him, hee hath garnished the high excellent woorkes of his wiſdom and hee is from euerlaſting to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtyng.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <pb facs="tcp:19400:34"/>
            <head>¶ The .x. Flower.</head>
            <p>NEwneſſe of life, and ſingleneſſe of hart, and an vndefiled waye, are the very offringes of ſoote incenſe vnto thée, O thou moſte righteous God, and thou accepteſt the ſorowful ſute of a martyred minde, in what time ſoeuer hee powreth foorthe his playnt vnto thee, ſo harken vnto mée I béeſéeche thee, for heauineſſe hath builded his bower within my breaſt.</p>
            <p>I come vnto thée béetimes in the mornyng, and late in the night, and at high noone, and when I go to reſt and when I riſe agayne, when I am alone, and when I am in companie, whether I bée in thy holly church, or in my ſecret chamber, and all is for thy mercie, O Lorde, for thou haſte no reſpecte of the perſon, time, or place.</p>
            <p>Multiplie in mée the giftes of thy
<pb facs="tcp:19400:35"/>grace, and conuert thy foes through my force, make my bodie an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all goodneſſe, whiche ſhall come to paſſe: if thou clenſe the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleaneſſe of my ſoule, ſcoure the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéemely ſpottes of my ſtayned con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, examine my thoughtes, and innouate a newe degrée of deſiers within my harte.</p>
            <p>Lorde, graunt I beſeeche thée, that whether I bee in wealth or woe, in health or in ſickeneſſe, whether I eat or drinke, ſleepe or wake, trauayle or take my reſt, or what euer I doo: I may doo it in thée, and for thée, and by thée, and nothing without thée, for my defier is alwaies, if it bée poſſible to bée with thee, &amp; neuer to bee from thee.</p>
            <p>Plant faſt thy pleaſure in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of my breaſt, for thy will, O God, is the worker of my wealthe, and my wil is the weauer of my wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy law is the leader vnto light, and
<pb facs="tcp:19400:35"/>my law is the loſer of my life, thy heaſtes are the healpers vnto health, and my heaſtes are the heapers vp of my heauineſſe, thy precepts are the porte of peace, and my preceptes are the paſſedge to perdition.</p>
            <p>This worlde where I am, Lorde, may well bée termed the vale of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, for héere is nothyng els but pride, malice, partialitie, trouble, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie, vexation, ſtrife, carefulneſſe, am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, couetouſneſſe, briberie, extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, vſurie, idle othes, and abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable periuirie, whoredome, hipocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and all vnclenlineſſe, bitter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention for the trueth of thy woorde: and no man careth to follow it.</p>
            <p>O Lorde, that it might pleaſe thee to quenche the thirſt of this worldly vanitie that biteth ſo ſharpe within the breaſt of mortall men, that they might ſee what it is that they ſeeke for, &amp; learne to looke after that which thei loſe, that by due conference of the
<pb facs="tcp:19400:36"/>twayne: they may beeholde their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and hartely repent them while they haue reſpite.</p>
            <p>The gayne of thy grace, O thou greate God, ſhall euermore bée the brightneſſe of my bewtie, for I will requeſt nothyng but thy mercie, and put my confidence in no creature but in thee only, if I haue that: then am I happie, and if I bee with thee: I am bleſſed, and I wil ſinge foorth thy prayſes in the congregation of thy faithfull people.</p>
            <p>Lorde, thou knoweſt how litle the righteouſneſſe is whiche I haue, and yet that whiche I haue is altogether to bee reputed thine, for it is euident that I can alonely doo no good deede, but not ſo mutche as name
<hi>GOD,</hi> were it not through the holly ghoſte, and vnleſſe thou giue the power, whiche ſayeſt that without thee wee can doo nothynge.</p>
            <p>Open my mouthe, that withall
<pb facs="tcp:19400:36"/>my ſoule I may make humble ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications vnto thee, and confeſſe my ſelfe vnto thy maieſtie, ſaying: thou haſt wrought all our good woorkes in vs, and therefore in reſpect of them wee may ſing with thy princely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Dauid, not vnto vs Lorde, not vnto vs, but vnto thy name giue the glorie.</p>
            <p>So farre as in mée lieth, I wil en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour, that thy moſt woorthie fame ſhall ſtreatche vnto the endes of the worlde, vnto Turkes, and infidels, that haue no knowledge of thee, or ſuch as liue in miſbeeleef of thy truth and I beeſéech thee to arme the prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chers of thy woord with boldnes, and vnderſtanding, that they may fayle for no feare, to tell the truth, nor bée corrupt with ignorance, nor hereſie.</p>
            <p>Thou art moſt woorthie, O lorde God, to bée loued and honoured, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r thy great goodnes and vnſearcheable wiſedome, and all other perfections
<pb facs="tcp:19400:37"/>without number or end, that art ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie perfection it ſelf, and all that euer wée can yéeld vnto thée, in faithe, or feare, or loue: is too too litle and very nothing in reſpect of that which thou haſt deſerued.</p>
            <p>If thou ſhouldeſt lay vnto our charge, the gréeuous default of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie, and righteouſneſſe, whiche is required to bee in vs, by thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes: O Lorde, how coulde wee endure the ſharpeneſſe of thy iudgement? for wée were aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to periſh eternally, but lende mée the ſhield of thy mercy, to defend mée againſt the ſtroake of thy iuſt wrath.</p>
            <p>Reueale vnto mine eyes the bew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and coomlineſſe of vertues, and the fowleneſſe and deformitie of vices, that I may fall in loue with the one, and miſlikyng with the other, taking a ſpeciall reguarde whiche I ſhoulde harbour in my hart, ſubmittyng my ſelf vnto thy heauenly diſpoſition, as
<pb facs="tcp:19400:37"/>I may bée made meeteſt to ſerue thée.</p>
            <p>I will laude thée, O Lorde my ſtrength, with my lippes, and I will magnifie thy might with my mouth, I wil loue thy lawes as my life, and walke in thy will as my way, I wil ſinge foorth thi ſaluation in my ſong, and muſe on thy mercies in my minde, I will hange vp thy hope in my harte, and bury thy bountie in my boſome.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="piece">
            <head>N.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>¶ Now I ſee that they which feare God haue the right ſpirite, for their hope ſtandeth in him that can helpe them: and the eies of the Lorde are on them that loue him.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <pb facs="tcp:19400:38"/>
            <head>¶ The .xj. Flower.</head>
            <p>NEuer let mée doo the thynge, O Lorde, that is diſpleaſant in thy ſight, but make thou my ſteppes right vnto thée, and cléere my pathes in thy preſence, that there bée no ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie founde in my harte, nor guile in my mouth, nor vnrighteouſneſſe in my handes, nor any thynge about mée that maye prouoke offence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt thee, that thou ſhouldeſt turn from mée, and forſake mée.</p>
            <p>It is thy wiſdome that is vnto mee more precious then golde, and I deſier it aboue althynges bee they neuer ſo fayer, I am inflamed with the loue of it, lende it vnto mée, my deere God, for it is that whiche tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth thy will, and ſheweth what is moſt acceptable vnto thy ſight, and it leadeth the way vnto the true wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhippynge of thee.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19400:38"/>O my God, I haue gone aſtray, I haue doone amiſſe, I haue commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted wickedneſſe, I am ſinfull, cal mée home, and pardon my miſdooynges, plucke mee away from my haynous offences, heale my ſoule that is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with harmes, for I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge my manifolde iniquities, and I am hartely ſorie for my ſinnes.</p>
            <p>I am woe that euer I went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrie, thou ſeeſt, Lord, the contrition of my hart, and my ſighing is not hid from thée, take no reguarde to my crimes that are paſt, but harken how I purpoſe to amende, only guide mée with thy grace, ſhunne not the ſute of a ſinner, but heare the prayer of him that putteth his truſt in thee, as thou moſt louingly haſt promiſed.</p>
            <p>Thou art almightie, O Lorde my God, and canſt graunt whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is aſked, giue vnto my ſoule an hartie féelyng of true deuotion, fulfill mée with the Charitie, and louynge
<pb facs="tcp:19400:39"/>kindeneſſe of thy deere ſunne, which hee expreſſed when moſte humbly hée offred himſelfe vpon the Croſſe, died the bitter death, and ſhedde his precious bloud for the ſinnes of mee, and many.</p>
            <p>Lorde, if my teares were in quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie match to the déepe ſea, and my ſighes were as the ſmoke of a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace, and my ſobbes coulde breake the harde Diamonde, and my way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynges were equall vnto the noyſe of thundre, and my ſorow were ſutch as no tongue can expreſſe: yet could I not ſufficiently lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for the guilt of my gréeuous offences.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt giuen mee an harte to vnderſtande thee, and eies to béehold thee in thy woorthie woorkes, giue mée alſo, I pray thee, a deſier to walke in thy will, and then I am certayne I ſhall want nothynge that is needefull for the good eſtate of my bodie or ſoule, aboue all, giue mée the
<pb facs="tcp:19400:39"/>quietneſſe of a calme conſcience, and ſeperate mée not from the hope of thy health.</p>
            <p>I haue prayed vnto thee, my ſwéet God, for perfection of minde, ſo I béeſéeche thée alſo, ſende mée the ſtrength and firmitude of bodie, with al the powers therof to thy pleaſure, preſerue the corporal life of my ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, thy faithfull ſeruant, our gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious gouerner: likewiſe of my pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes, friendes, and kinſefolke, voucheſaulfe to bée fauourable vnto my feere whom thou haſt ſent mée in thy feare, and ſtande good father vnto my poore remainder, the béeloued moitie of my life.</p>
            <p>If thou graunt not my petitions, thou art true notwithſtandyng, for God heareth not ſinners, and if thou giue eare vnto my prayers, thou art merciful, for thou commaundeſt mée to aſke and I ſhall receaue, and if I obtayne: it is only thy méere libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie
<pb facs="tcp:19400:40"/>no deſert of mine, ſhew mée thy mercie that I may bee hearde, and make mee worthy, O Lorde, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt taught mée to pray, O deliuer mée from the greate éeuill, ſaue mée from the mouth of the mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Dragon whiche continually proſecuteth mée, and with the ſheild of thy might deliuer mée from his perilous hornes, for his moſt gréedy deſier is to entrappe my life, and to deuoure my ſoule whiche thou haſte created.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, O Lorde, inceſſantly I crie vnto thee, acquite mee from my daylie aduerſarie, whiche, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I ſleepe or wake, whether I eate or drinke, or whatſoeuer I doo: by all meanes bothe day and night, lieth in waite priuely or openly to ſhoote his venemous ſhaftes againſt mee, and to ſley my ſoule, but bee thou my gracious protectour.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19400:40"/>If thou, Lorde, bée on my ſide: I eſtéeme not the force of any foe, there is nothynge to hurt where thou arte to helpe, there can no fende of darck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe impugne, where the Lorde of light doth defende, let mée not periſh, Lorde, through lacke of thy ſuccour, for in my hart I haue made thee the full refuge of my hope, and the ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier of my health.</p>
            <p>Confeſſe I muſt néedes, that the deuiſes of my hart haue driuen mee from my duetie, and the imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of my minde haue augmented my miſcheif, but I truſt, Lorde, that in the ritchneſſe of thy mercies thou wilt thinke on my pouertie, and in the plentie of thy goodneſſe thou wilt remembre my ſcarcitie of perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and take fauourable compaſſion vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon mee.</p>
            <p>O eternall Lorde, I powre not foorthe my prayers béefore thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, truſtynge in the ſtrength of
<pb facs="tcp:19400:41"/>mine owne righteouſneſſe: but in thy greate and manifolde mercies, ſaue mée, Lorde, for thy déere ſonnes ſake, preſerue mée from ſlaundrous tungues, and hatefull hartes, defende mée from miſhappe, peſtilence, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, murther, and ſudden death I béeſéeche thee.</p>
            <p>I will ſinge with my mouth, and giue thankes with my harte, and ſet foorth thy glorie, moſt glorious God, and I will conforme all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of my body that they ſhall doo thy will, I wil bee wholy the Lords and the Lorde ſhalbee the porcion of my patrimonie, refuſe mée not, for my will ſhall alwayes bée with thée.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="piece">
            <pb facs="tcp:19400:41"/>
            <head>E.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>¶ Euery mans woorke shalbeo made manifeſt, the day ſhall declare it, bicauſe it ſhalbee reuealed by the fier, and the fier ſhall trie euerie mans woorke what it is.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <head>¶ The .xij. Flower.</head>
            <p>EVerlaſtyng God, and moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Father, thou haſte ſtirred mée vp with the liuely feelyng of an vnfayned faith, this day to call vpon thy moſt holly name, increaſe, I bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéethe thee, continually that godly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier within my breaſt, for I know thou haſt guiftes enow in ſtore for vs all, and thou wilt heare the humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of an hartie praier.</p>
            <p>Heare mée now therefore, O my Lorde, for I ſtande a far of criynge with the <hi>Publican,</hi> Lorde haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie
<pb facs="tcp:19400:42"/>vpon mée which am a ſinner, and with the Leaper, Lorde if it bée thy will: thou canſt clenſe mée, and with the faithfull <hi>Centurian,</hi> Lorde my ſeruant is very ſicke and like to die, but ſay thou the woorde and hée ſhall bée made whole.</p>
            <p>What doo théeſe woordes ſignifie other, O Lorde, but that I am in miſerie and fayne woulde bée relée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, I am in ſorow and fayne would bée comforted, I am in diſtreſſe and fayne woulde bee ſuccoured, I am in ſinne and fayne woulde bée pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and I come vnto thee, for thou art the only woorker of wealth, and Lorde of mercie, and I hope thou wilt helpe mée.</p>
            <p>Haue mercie vpon mée, O Lorde, haue mercie vpon mée, for I had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo mutche néede, my offences are increaſed, and my force is diminiſhed a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d if I would take in hand to write the millians of my miſdeedes, that
<pb facs="tcp:19400:42"/>dayly doo burden my bodie, and ſinke my ſoule: it were néedeful that thou ſhouldeſt create in mee a thouſande new toongues.</p>
            <p>I can hide nothyng from thée, that whiche I haue committed in ſecrete: lieth manifeſt béefore thy celeſtiall eyes, for at the dooynge of all thynges thou art preſent, and thou art the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall bee holder of my harte, and all my delightes, déedes, and deuiſes of minde, are as cleare in thy ſight: as is the light of the nooneday, and more clearer.</p>
            <p>But harken now awhile, O my ſoule, forſake thy worldly buſineſſe, and carefull cogitations for a ſeaſon, bée at leaſure vnto God, and take thy reſt in him, entre into the ſecret clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet of thy harte, and ſhut foorth all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther occupations, and when thou art there alone: then ſéeke for the lorde, and hée will ſéeke for thée, and if thou liſt: thou ſhalt ſurely finde him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19400:43"/>And when thou haſt founde him: ſay then vnto him, O lorde, my harte hath ſought thy face, teache mée, I béeſéeche thée, how I may ſéeke thee aright, and where I may finde thee readely, if thou bée abſent where I may haue thée preſent, if I cannot ſe thée, for darkeneſſe of my vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng: brynge mée into the inacceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble light, where I may alwayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde thee.</p>
            <p>Lorde, what ſhall thy ſeruant doo whiche languiſheth for the loue of thée, and pineth for payne that hée is ſo longe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy preſence? hée would gladly finde thée: and hée woteth not the place of thy abode, hée would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyngly ſeeke thee: and hée knoweth not thy face, yet art thou my Lorde, and my God, and I the worke of thy worthy handes.</p>
            <p>O mightie God, thou haſte made mée, and preſerued mée, and thou diddeſt create mée that I ſhould bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde
<pb facs="tcp:19400:43"/>thee, and yet haue I not fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led that for whiche I was ordeyned. O how miſerable is the ſtate, and condition of mankinde, if hée loſe that through his owne wilfulneſſe, for whiche hée was made? let mée neuer Lorde, ſée that day, but ſhew mee the light of thy glorie.</p>
            <p>Make mée recompt, O Lorde, through thee, the miſerie of mine owne tranſgreſſions, and with woon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull affection to deſier redreſſe at thy deitie, how all the children of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam ſhould haue fead on the bread of Angels at pleaſure, which now they doo want, and now they breake the bread of ſorow, wheron they feede at full with all bitterneſſe.</p>
            <p>Forget not thy poore creature, O moſt merciful God, that is buried vp in mountaynes of miſerie, and ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp in the ſea of ſorow, turne thy face vnto mée whiche was tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned away from mée, and heare mée
<pb facs="tcp:19400:44"/>whom thou wouldeſt not beeholde, lighten my dimmed eies, and ſhew mee thy cheerefull countenance.</p>
            <p>Reſtore thy ſelfe vnto mée, that it may goe well with mée in thée, with whom it goeth ſo ill without thee, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payer my decayed partes, take pitie vpon my afflictions and traueiles, helpe mine endeuours, for I can doo nothyng without thee, ſweeten my bitter potion with thy celeſtiall ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, ſuffer mée not to die in deſpay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge: but to haue life in hopyng.</p>
            <p>In hart and contemplation, Lord, I draw néere vnto thee, a carefull caſtaway pining with pouertie: vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee the Lorde of light waltrynge in wealth, a miſerable wretche: to a mercifull God, an hungrie ſoule to the fountayne of foode, Lorde, I haue ſought thée hungrynge, let mée not leaue thee faſtyng, nor departe from thee fayntyng.</p>
            <p>Teache mée the way, ſweet God,
<pb facs="tcp:19400:44"/>wherein I may walke to ſeeke thee, and ſhew thy ſelfe vnto mee, I bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeche thee, that faine woulde finde thee, for I cannot ſeeke thee vnleſſe thou inſtruct mee, nor I cannot finde thee: vnleſſe thou diſcrie thy ſelf, let mee ſeeke thee in deſieryng, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier thee in ſeeking, let mée finde thée in louyng, and loue thee in findyng.</p>
            <p>As I am thine Image: ſo make mee remembre my ſelfe, to thynke on thee with loue, loue thee with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier, deſier thee with feare, feare thee with faith, ſeeke thee with wiſdome, finde thee with truth and ſingleneſſe of hart, and abide with thee in thyne eternall glorie, whiche thou haſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for them that ſerue thee.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="piece">
            <pb facs="tcp:19400:45"/>
            <head>B</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>¶ Bleſſe them whiche perſecute you, bleſſe, and curſe not, reioyce with them that reioyce, and weepe with them that weepe, beeing of like af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection one vnto another, not high minded, but matching your ſelues to the lower ſorte.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <head>¶ The .xiij. Flower.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Leſſed are they, as</hi> thou haſt taught vs, O my ſweete ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Ieſus Chriſte, which diligently doo heare thy moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy woord: and kéepe the ſame, yea thriſe bleſſed are they that ſpende their time in the ſearche of thy right ſacred will, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing
<pb facs="tcp:19400:45"/>it in their life and conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for thy holly ſpirite ſhall neuer bée abſent from them.</p>
            <p>I woulde to God it might pleaſe thee, ſo to addreſſe my waies, that I might in no wiſe wander awrie, and that thou wouldeſt take away all ſtumblinge blockes from my feete that I might not fall, and preuent all daungers that I might not miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carie, but that thy pathes were made ſo plaine: that I might neuer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit offence againſt thee.</p>
            <p>O Lorde, ſo it irketh mee that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer I went aſtray, it greeueth mee to the hart, inſomutch that I can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue no comfort when I thinke on thy heauie wrath, and due indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion wherwith thou doeſt proſecute the ſinnes of the vngodlie, eeuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the third and fouerth generation of ſutch as haue not fulfilled thi com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes.</p>
            <p>But bée thou, good Lord, vnto mee
<pb facs="tcp:19400:46"/>a moſt ſpeciall comforter, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I bée alreadie laid verie low: yet I may not bée vtterly brought to ruine, turne the bitter ſcourge of thy welwoorthie vengeance, leaſt I periſh in the ſharpe execution of thy deſerued puniſhment, and ſo that bée loſt which thou dideſt make, and buie full déere.</p>
            <p>Thy propertie it is, moſte bleſſed God, to ſaue and not to ſpil, thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt create and not conſume, thy woorkes are wondrous, and they ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med al good vnto thée, when thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt make nothynge of ſpight, nor ſpight at nothyng that thou diddeſt make, whereby increaſeth my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that I ſhall not bée left quight deſtitute, and forſaken.</p>
            <p>It is affliction enough for mée, that I haue forſaken thy waies, and not looked after the Lorde of my life, let confeſſion of the fault bee ſufficient puniſhment for an offender y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſeth
<pb facs="tcp:19400:46"/>not of ſet purpoſe, but onely through the imperfection of frayle nature, and want of thy moſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous goodneſſe.</p>
            <p>I haue broken thy ſtatutes like a proude rebell, I haue contemned thy preceptes like a naughtie ſeruant, I haue violated thy will like a diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient childe, I haue wandred from thy folde like a loſt ſhéepe, I haue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obeyed the good pleaſure of my moſt ſweete and louyng God: like a moſt wicked, and wretched creature.</p>
            <p>Deale not with mée, O Lorde, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge vnto my deſertes but thy kindeneſſe, not hauyng reſpect vnto ſeuere iuſtice, but tendre mercies: that I may liue lenger to amend my miſdeedes, and other by mine exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may endeuour to doo the like, and ſo thy moſt noble name may be mag<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nified bothe in them and mée, with right woorthy commendation.</p>
            <p>Let not that bée layed vnto my
<pb facs="tcp:19400:47"/>charge, I hartly béeſéeche thée, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in vnwittyng, vnwillyng, or vnadui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly I haue prouoked thy anger, but forget the follies of my forepaſſed yéeres, when I was yonge and raſh by courſe of kinde, when ſinne is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coumpted but a play, and but very ſmale reguarde is hadde vnto thy wayes.</p>
            <p>Purifie mée from my ſecret ſinnes wherof there is none priuie but thou alonely, that ſitteſt on high, and ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſt the priuities of eche mans hart béelow in the earthe, to iudge euery one in his owne deuiſe, and repaye them accordyng vnto their inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, béewraying their filthineſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the worlde, that erſt lay ſecret in couert.</p>
            <p>O Lorde, for thy names ſake, let no cuſtome of ſinnyng take holde vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon mee, nor let mée neuer take plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure in dooynge wickedneſſe, for the one were harde to bée eſchewed with
<pb facs="tcp:19400:47"/>out ſpeciall helpe, and the other is a manifeſt ſigne of want of grace, but bée thou alwayes my ſuccour, O thou the God of my ſtrength, and fortitude.</p>
            <p>Suffre vs not to goe a whoorynge with ſtraunge thinges, whilſt wee ſeeke after thee, as for thee: thou art within vs if wée wilbée within thee, wee neede not to ſearche thée far of: for thou art with vs in our fayth, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till ſutche time as wée deſerue that thou maiſt bee with vs in perſonall apparance, which graunt that I may beeholde.</p>
            <p>For wée know, as ſayeth the holly Apoſtle, that Chriſte through faythe dothe dwell within our hartes. For why? Chriſte is within our Faith, the faith within our minde, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> minde within our hart, the hart within our breaſt, but clenſe thou them all, moſt gratious God, that my bodie may bée made a méete temple for thee to
<pb facs="tcp:19400:48"/>dwell in.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt faſſhioned mee after thyne owne image, conforme mee therefore my God, moſt likely vnto thy ſimilitude, in all vertue, and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, in deſier of peace, in contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of veritie, in loue of charitie, let mée euermore retayne thee in memorie, carie thée in my conſcience holde thee in my harte, and honour thee as preſent.</p>
            <p>Heare mee, O God, in thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp; turne not thy mercifull eare from my ſorowfull crie, O let the vncleaneſſe of my ſoule bee purified, the darckeneſſe of my minde light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the warmeneſſe of my harte heatened, the coldeneſſe of my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence warmed, and the ſleepineſſe of my bodie wakened, and I my ſelf by all meanes prepared, that I may bée thy ſeruant to doo thy heauenly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as I am alreadie the woorke of thy cunninge fingers.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="piece">
            <pb facs="tcp:19400:48"/>
            <head>A</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>¶ A man that beareth hatred againſt another, how dare hee deſier for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of God? forgiue then thy neighbour the hurt that hee hath doone thee, and ſo ſhall thy ſinnes bee forgiuen thee alſo when thou praieſt.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <head>¶ The .xiiij. Flower.</head>
            <p>ADuaunce thyſelf, O Lorde, in thine eternall power, and draw thée néere to deliuer mee from the ſnares of the Deuill, that haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trapped mée, and throwne mée al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt vnto the grownd, I haue bin plunged a longe time in the ſea of ſenſualitie, and I perceaue my deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce cometh only from thée, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deliuer mée, O Lorde, of my ſaluation.</p>
            <p>Thy power is aboue all powers,
<pb facs="tcp:19400:49"/>thou haſt made althynges ſubiect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thée, for through thée Death hath no ſtinge, nor Hell hath victorie, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall thankes bée vnto God, who in our good Lorde, and ſauiour Ieſus Chriſte: hath giuen vnto vs a noble co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>queſt euer our enemies, for which while I liue: I wil giue moſt woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy prayſe, as it beſt béeſeemeth.</p>
            <p>Henceforward looke thou carefully vnto the courſe of my life, and holde faſt my harte alwayes in thy feare, that I bée not founde vnwoorthy of thy moſte bountifull benefittes, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in mée a care to continue in thy commaundements, erecte a fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent faith and aſſured hope of thy promiſes, and mercie, within the tendre intrayles of my breaſt.</p>
            <p>Sprinckle my hart with a dreadge of thy compaſſion and precepts min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled togither, that I may not wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der aſide, nor fall into the gulf of thy wrath, but thy fauour may ſuſtayne
<pb facs="tcp:19400:49"/>mee, and thy loue may lift mee vp, bryngyng my féete into thy roomthe of reſt, where I may not chooſe but fulfill thy godly heaſtes.</p>
            <p>O, how happie were I, if I might neuer héereafter in thought, woorde, nor déede, commit the thynge that ſhould diſpleaſe thy maieſtie? that life is the longyng of my ſoule, and th'effect of my deſier, my hart mutch wiſheth to ſée that bleſſed time, and my ioyes then ſhould bée ſutch as no toongue can tell.</p>
            <p>Truely, to know thée, with the Sunne, and the holly ghoſt: is the true perfection of eternall life, th'end of bliſſefulneſſe, the ſumme of all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightes, no eye hath ſéene, no eare hath heard, nor hath it pearced into the deapth of any mans vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng, to valew the ineſtéemable cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, delectation, and pleaſures of the ſame felicitie, when wée ſhall béehold the maieſtie of God face to face.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19400:50"/>Verely, moſte glorious kinge, I haue repoſed this hope in my boſom, and my harte daunceth within my breaſt for ioy therof, and I doo aſſure my ſelfe, through faith in thée, that theſe eyes wherewith I reade theſe lines: ſhall ſée that glorie, and this fleaſh wherwith I am cloked in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and meaſhed in mortalitie: ſhalbee a membre of that immortall kyngdome.</p>
            <p>This worlde is farſt with wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and there are manie ſtaies that ſtoppe a man from righteouſneſſes, blindyng him that hée may not ſee, and hampryng him that hée may not ſtirre to doo the thyng that is accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto God, ſequeſtring his minde from all thoughtes, ſtudies, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours that may incite him vnto thée.</p>
            <p>But my truſt is in thée, O God, that thou wilt not ſuffer mée to fall into any outragious offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that may demerite thy hot indignation, O
<pb facs="tcp:19400:50"/>turne away mine eyes, leaſt I bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde vanitie, and guide my handes that I tutche no vniuſt thyng, lift vp my mynde vnto contemplation of heauenly ſightes, and pull mée from terreſtriall cogitations that are but tranſitorie.</p>
            <p>I haue prayed for one thynge, and I requeſt the ſame moſte hartely, that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wouldeſt preſerue my youthe from flatterers, and mine olde age from ſlaunderers, for the one ſorte of them would deuoure mée béefore I am ripe, and the other would burie mée béefore I am dead, and I haue alwayes hated them bothe vtterly.</p>
            <p>Powre downe vpon mée, O my louyng God, the bleſſed dew of thy diuine and incomparable wiſdome, whiche is alwayes reſident aboute thy heauenly ſeat, that I may know my ſelfe throughly, and honour thée woorthely, conſideryng the frame of mine owne infirmitie, and that there
<pb facs="tcp:19400:51"/>is no goodneſſe but it deſcendeth from thee that arte aboue.</p>
            <p>When, through the peruerſe, and froward inclination of my nature, I fall into any wicked, and vngodly i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginations: leaue mée not, good Lorde, vnto them, acquite mée from the diſordinate luſtes of the body, let no deſier of vncleaneſſe take holde vpon mee, and giue mée not ouer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an vnſhamefaſt, impious, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate minde.</p>
            <p>Set a ſure bridle vpon my mouth, that I ſpeake no proude thynges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt thée, ſuffer not my toongue to bée acquaincted with ſwearyng, and let not the namyng of God bée conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually in my lippes, for in it are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie falles, but mercifully giue thou mée aduiſement what I ſhal ſpeake, ere euer I open my mouth.</p>
            <p>Call not the woordes that I haue vaynely ſpoken vnto accoumpt, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute them not vnto mée for ſinne,
<pb facs="tcp:19400:51"/>giue mée vnderſtandynge to keepe prudent ſilence, and when I ſpeake let it either bée for temporall neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, either to edefie others, or els to beare righteous teſtimonie of the trueth, let the veritie of my aſſertion conſiſt in yea yea, or nay nay.</p>
            <p>Lorde, héere ſtande I vile wretch béefore the throne of thy drad pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, hopyng that I ſhalbée heard, not in the fayntneſſe of my faith: but in the power of thy promiſes. O weigh my weakeneſſe, and graunt my deſier, as thou knoweſt moſte méete for mée, then can I want no wealth, and my conſcience ſhalbée re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhed with all ſpirituall conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="piece">
            <pb facs="tcp:19400:52"/>
            <head>C</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>¶ Caſt not thine eyes aſide from the poore, that thou giue him no occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to ſpeake euill of thee. For if hee complayne in the bitterneſſe of his ſoule: his praier ſhalbee heard, euen hee that made him, ſhal heare him.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <head>¶ The .xv. Flower.</head>
            <p>CHaſten mée, O God, howbéeit, not in the conſumyng rage of thy ielous wrath, for then ſhall I vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly periſh, but temper, I béeſéeche thee, thy fury with compaſſion, to the redreſſe of my life, not confuſion of my ſoule, for if thou ſhouldeſt deale ſo ſeuerely with ſinners: alas, what ſhould béecome of them? for there is no fleaſh righteous in thy ſight.</p>
            <p>O, thinke mercifully vppon the
<pb facs="tcp:19400:52"/>auncient ſore of our ſinnes, how that vnwittyngly wée are coneaued and borne in iniquitie, and bée thou rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to apply the ſalue of thy mercie, the onely remedie of Adams infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted frute, wherby our wekned bones are made ſtronge, and wée are eft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoones erected into thy fauour.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt layde thine heauie diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure vpon mée, whiche I know well my wickedneſſe hath deſerued, namely a careleſſe conſcience, and necligent callyng vpon thée for grace and thou haſt opened mine eyes that I might béeholde my miſerie, and how far I am caried from thee, that art the port of my ſaluation.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtandyng thy roddes, and thy ſtaues, O Lorde, wherwith thou haſt beaten mée haue brought mee comfort, thy correction is full of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, and in the midſt of the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries whiche deſeruedly thou heapeſt vpon our heads: thou groneſt at our
<gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:19400:53"/>plagues, what due damnation deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth ſutche demeanure?</p>
            <p>Agayne, O moſte vnſpeakeable mercie of thy diuine goodneſſe, that béeholdeſt vs dayly turnynge away our vnhappie eares, ſhuttynge our fooliſh eyes, hardning our ſtubburne hartes, and yet notwithſtandynge crieſt vnto vs, O yée ſinners, incline vnto wiſdome, and béeholde, for I am the Lorde your God.</p>
            <p>Mercifull God, if at any time I haue bin ſutche one: I hartely bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéeche thée not to impute it vnto mée, forgiue mée all my fonde negligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and groſſe ignorancies whiche I haue left vndoone, let them come no more into thy ſight to bée obiected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt mée.</p>
            <p>O, how well were I, if it might pleaſe thée to draw mée a direct line in thy lawes, that I might goe right, and leade mée in the light of thy tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that I might not trippe, and hold
<pb facs="tcp:19400:53"/>mée by the hande that I might not fall, but eſpecially if thou wouldeſt take mée vnto thée, that wheras thou art, I might bée euer there alſo?</p>
            <p>I haue meruelouſly offended thée, and there are manie occaſions of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, whiche if thou wouldeſt take from mée: then ſhould not my ſinnes bée ſo burdenous vnto my ſoule, nor ſo gréeuous vnto thy ſight, whiche I confeſſe are manifold, but, Lorde, I know thy mercie, and ſauyng health are infinite, and thou art prone vnto forgiueneſſe.</p>
            <p>The ripeneſſe of my perfection: ſhalbée the gréeneſſe of thy glorie, the Summer of my ſutes: ſhalbée the ſpryng of thy prayſe, the harueſt of my righteouſneſſe: ſhalbee the ſéede of thy commendation, the winter of my wickedneſſe: ſhalbée the earyng of thy honour, the frutes of my faith: ſhalbée the flower of thy worthineſſe the toppe of my tranquillitie: ſhalbée
<pb facs="tcp:19400:54"/>the roote of thy renowme.</p>
            <p>I will walke in thy wayes, O Lorde, and obey thy will, I will kéep thy commaundementes and take care of thy couenantes, I will holde thy heaſtes as my life and reguarde thy preceptes as mine owne ſoule, there ſhall nothyng thruſt mée from thy trueth, nor fray mée from thy feare, nor allure mee from thy loue, and then am I as certayn that I ſhal liue: as I am ſure thy prayſes ſhall not die.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="piece">
            <head>O</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>¶ O giue eare vnto good counſell, and bee content to bee reformed, that thou maiſt bee wiſe hereafter: for there are manie deuiſes in a mans hart, neuertheleſſe the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of the Lorde ſhall ſtande for euer.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <pb facs="tcp:19400:54"/>
            <head>¶ The .xvj. Flower.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> Lorde, thou Father and <hi>GOD</hi> of my life, I béeſeeche thée, for thy ſunne Chriſtes ſake, bend down thine eyes of compaſſion vpon mée that am thine humble ſeruant, but at this preſente wofully oppreſſed with careful incumbrances of ſinne, ſo that I want power to lift vp my handes, and with my tongue I am not able to expreſſe the ſorowes that I ſuſtayne.</p>
            <p>I am déepely wounded that my life languiſheth away, I am broken that I cannot recouer, I am ſore that I cannot bée cured, I am ſicke that I cannot bée ſaued, I am ſo nighe death that I cannot liue, I am ſo pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: that I am paſt al helpe, vnleſſe that thou, O Lorde, come with ſpée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die reléeife, the worker of my wealth and curer of all infirmities.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19400:55"/>For, if thou put foorthe thy hollie hande: I ſhalbée holpen, if thou doo tutche mée: I ſhalbée ſaued, if thou doo but ſay the woorde: my lothſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhalbée releeued. O Lorde, I pray thee hartely come eaſe mée of my gréeifes, come cure mée of my care, come ſaue mée from my ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, come aſſure me from my ſores reſtore mee to my health, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longe the dayes of my life to thy pleaſure.</p>
            <p>In weakeneſſe of bodie and infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of minde, in feebleneſſe of fleſh and craſineſſe of conſcience, in aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of the worlde and all miſeries of mankinde: I haue made mine er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt complaynt vnto thee, O Lorde, and thou haſt graciouſly heard mee, thou diddeſt neuer turne from mee in proſperitie, nor diſdayne mée in trouble, and I truſt thou wilt neuer forſake mée.</p>
            <p>Lorde, this worlde is ſubiect vnto
<pb facs="tcp:19400:55"/>meruelous mutabilitie, the ſtate of men is variable, for thou enritcheſt the poore, &amp; empoueriſheſt the ritch, thou pulleſt downe the loftie, and rayſeſt vp the baſe, yet graunt vnto mée, that I may with all meekenes of minde bée well contented with the callyng wherunto thou haſt alotted mée, and yéelde vnto thée moſte due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull thankes therefore.</p>
            <p>Giue not vnto mée, O God, the great heapes of worldly wealth, nor caſt not vpon mée the gnawyng pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of pininge pouertie, for ritches make a man not know himſelfe, mutcheleſſe God, and pouertie, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie times, is an enemie vnto verte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous maners and godlineſſe, but mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully graunt vnto mée a reſonable competent liuing.</p>
            <p>There are many that haue fallen by abundance, and diuerſe by lacke, but, O thou heauenly Father, that art only the ritche God: vouchſaulf,

<pb facs="tcp:19400:56"/>I beeſeeche thee, to giue mée alwaies a ſufficient relieuynge bothe for my body and ſoule, and for the charge of houſeholde whiche thou haſt giuen vnto mee, and in althynges to auoid moſt vayne ſuperfluitie.</p>
            <p>Sweete Lorde, fixe my minde firmely vpon thee and nothyng els, as for worldly things let them ſéeme vile vnto mee in reſpect of thee, let mee take comfort in thee and not in them, ſuffer no mirth to remayne in my minde, nor ioy to harbour in my harte, nor pleaſure to reſt in my thought, nor deſier to abide in my breaſt: that is not in thee, and for thee only.</p>
            <p>If it bee thy will, O eternal kyng, that I ſhall liue in thy loue, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in thy fauour: take away from mee the meanes of ordinarie offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thee, make mee angrie without ſinning, humble without faynynge, merie without lightneſſe, ſad with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:19400:56"/>out miſtruſt, ſobre without dulneſſe, and truſtie without doubleneſſe.</p>
            <p>Strike into my harte a true feare of thee, yet that I doo not diſpayer, and a feruent loue vnto thee, but yet that I may not preſume, giue mee vnderſtandynge to amende myne owne vnrighteouſneſſe with diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and admoniſh my neighbours of their faultes without diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that by my woordes and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample they may take a paterne of doctrine, and liuinge.</p>
            <p>Eſtabliſh mée in a right trade of wel pleaſing thee, that my life may bée conformable vnto thy woorthie will, reueale vnto th'eies of my ſoule by inſpiration of the holly ſpirite, ſome ſight or taſte of thy heauenly ioyes, that I may bée caried with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to accompliſh that whiche is pleaſant vnto thée: and profitable for myne owne ſelfe.</p>
            <p>A droppe of thy grace: ſhalbée the
<pb facs="tcp:19400:57"/>ſea of my ſaluation, a ſparcle of thy loue: ſhalbée the flame of my fayth, a mote of thy mercie: ſhalbée the heape of my health, a ſande of thy ſight: ſhalbée the banke of my bew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, a grayne of thy goodneſſe: ſhalbée the weight of my woorthineſſe, one fauour of thy celeſtiall face: ſhalbée the fulneſſe of mine eternall felicitie.</p>
            <p>O Lorde God, and holly Father, caſt downe thine eyes from thy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred ſainctuarie, and from thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly habitation, and béeholde the moſt acceptable ſacrafice whiche our high biſhop Ieſus Chriſte, thy déere ſunne our Lorde, offreth vp vnto thy maieſtie for our manifolde ſinnes, and bée mercifull vnto the multitude of our miſdéedes.</p>
            <p>Béeholde, the precious blood of our moſt ſwéete Sauiour crieth yet vnto thée from the altar of the Croſſe, hee hangeth yet there, and ſtill is hée dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto thée, who ſéeſt althynge in
<pb facs="tcp:19400:57"/>preſent that bée paſt, &amp; béefore whoſe eyes the effectes of all times doone do euer abide as now in dooing, conſider him, O mercifull God, and for his ſake take pitie vpon vs.</p>
            <p>I muſt néedes loue thée, O my moſt déere redéemer Ieſus Chriſte, with all my hart, with all my ſoule, and with all my power, that diddeſt vouchſaulf to die for my ſinnes, my ſoule cleaueth faſt vnto thee, for thou art hir ſtrength and fortitude, graunt vnto mee, that I may enſue thy wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy ſteppes, and bée partaker of thy heauenly kingdome, accordyng as I haue ſhewen my ſighinges vnto thée and put my whole truſt in thée, that art the porcion of mine inheritance.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="piece">
            <pb facs="tcp:19400:58"/>
            <head>N</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>¶ Naked as wee came foorth of our moothers wombe: euen ſo goe wee hence agayne, and carie nothyng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with vs of all our labour. Conſider this woonderfull woorke of God, and how that no man can make the thynge ſtreight which hee maketh crooked.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <head>¶ The .xvij. Flower.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>NO</hi> creature vnder heauen may bryng mée comfort but thou, O Lorde of eternall glorie, that art the healpe of mans health, and ſurgeon of his ſoule, thou ſtrikeſt and healeſt, thou bringeſt a man nigh vnto death and anon reſtoreth him to life again, to th'intent hée may know his owne weakeneſſe and imbecillitie: &amp; cleaue the more firmely vnto thy ſtrength and vertue.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19400:58"/>As for man, hée is nothynge els but a ſhew of ſimple ſéede, and a ſlip of ſlender ſtrength, and a bubble of boylyng brothe, and a branche of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge flowers, and an handfull of goodly graſſe that to day flouriſheth in the fielde, and to morow is flunge into the fier, a frame of moſte frayle fleaſh, in whom is no perpetuitie nor endurance.</p>
            <p>Lorde, let mée euermore beare this portrature in my minde of mine owne infirmitie, conſiderynge ſtill what I am, remembryng alwayes what I would bée, then ſhall I léeſe likyng of my ſelfe: and longe after the loue of thee, for I am the image of thy ſubſtance, although the looking backe from thy lawes hath ſoyled mée ſore with ſinne.</p>
            <p>As I am ful of imperfection of my ſelfe: ſo ſupply thou my wantes in thee, for when I haue indeuoured al I may, my righteouſneſſe is thine,
<pb facs="tcp:19400:59"/>and thou crowneſt mée with endleſſe honour for that which procéedeth on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from thee, and is ſo litle agreeable vnto my corrupt nature: that it is rather quight, alas, repugnant.</p>
            <p>My ſinnes, O Lorde, lie foorth in plentie béefore my face, I can turne no way but they ouertake mée, I woulde faine intreate thee to pardon them and I dare not draw néere thee for dread of them, conſider my neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie moſt mightie God, and deliuer mée, and graunt moſt graciouſly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy ſinfull ſeruant: the participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thy moſt glorious maieſtie.</p>
            <p>What though my ſinnes bée as the ſandes of the ſea, and my wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſurmount the leaues of the woodde, and my tranſgreſſions ſtriue in numbre with the flowers of the ſprynge? yet take thou no reguarde, O Lorde, vnto the frowardneſſe of my hart, but like as thou haſt many times ſhewed mercie: ſo now bee
<pb facs="tcp:19400:59"/>pitifull, and forgiue mée.</p>
            <p>I haue hungred, my ſouereigne Lorde and God, to feede vpon thee that art the breade of life, not with the iawes of my fleaſh: but with the mouth of my faith, vntil it mai pleaſe thée to féede mée at full with the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire contemplation of thy ſubſtance, whiche I ſhall ſée face to face, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo bée ſéene in thy celeſtiall glorie, when I am diſcharged of this farthel of frailtie, this hope is the harbour of my delight, and the aſſured lookynge for it is the cheifeſt flower of my Garlande.</p>
            <p>Moſt gracious gouerner, giue mée to drinke of that water, wherof who ſo drinketh: ſhall thirſt the more, as after the ſwéeteneſſe of heauenly thynges, whoſe taſte is vnſpeakable pleaſant, and giue mée alſo to drinke of that water the drinkers whereof ſhall thirſt nomore for euer, for it floweth foorth from thée, the fountain
<pb facs="tcp:19400:60"/>of immortalitie.</p>
            <p>Truely Lorde, there is no cauſe, why I ſhould longe to abide in this life, if I were of ſutch perfection as was thy Apoſtle Paule: I ſhould perceaue the wickedneſſe of this worlde, and the glorie of thy kynge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and wiſhe erneſtly as hée did, to bée diſſolued from this body, and to bée with Chriſte, where as hée reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in eternitie.</p>
            <p>O Lorde, thou knoweſt my hartie deſier is alwaies to ſerue thee, grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto mée of thy gracious goodneſſe, that I may liue in thy law, and run in thy rule, and walke in thy way, and die in thy faith, and that I may bée cléerely deliuered of the bondage of ſinne, and bee wholy out of dreade of death and dampnation.</p>
            <p>Execute theſe thinges vpon mee, O my moſte louynge God, and as it ſhall ſeeme beſt vnto thy pleaſure, &amp; moſt ſittyng for my ſoule: abridge
<pb facs="tcp:19400:60"/>the dayes of this Pilgrimage, and commence the terme of my true life, call mée from this Clay, and clothe mée in the wéede of euerlaſtynge wealth, where thou art reſident with thy ſaynctes in eternall glorie.</p>
            <p>Lorde, if it ſo bée, that the deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion day of all fleaſh bée at hande, as it is hartely hoped: then haue wee great cauſe to yéelde thée moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thankes for ſhortning the time of our trouble and takyng away the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of offendyng, that thine elect may poſſeſſe the longer frute of their ioyes, and yéelde vp the ſummes of a ſhorter accoumpt.</p>
            <p>O God, what a ioyfull day ſhall that ſame bée, when wée ſhall bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde with our eyes thoſe thynges whiche wée haue often recorded in our hartes, and heare with our eares whiche wée haue read with our eies, and feele with our ſence that whiche wée haue manifoldly conceaued in
<pb facs="tcp:19400:61"/>our mindes, but all as it were in a cloude, or veyle, but then to enioye them in expreſſe, and perfect kinde?</p>
            <p>Mortefie the man of ſinne, I pray thée good Lorde, which reigneth with in my mortall body, that alwayes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belleth agaynſt my ſpirite, depreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge mee downe euer in ignorance, and enuiyng mée the fruition of thy noble bewtie, let no feare of any cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall death deterre mée from the moſte heauenly féelynge of ſutche a ghoſtly contemplation.</p>
            <p>If once the fulneſſe of this effect were brought vnto wiſſhed ende: wée ſhould not néede with ſutche de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier to make ſute for our ſinnes, for in thy kyngdome, O moſt pure god, there diuelleth no wickedneſſe nor infirmitie, but eche toongue is buſie in ſingyng thy prayſe, all laude and honour bée vnto thée, O moſt migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God, for euer and euer, worlde without ende.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="complaint">
            <pb facs="tcp:19400:61"/>
            <head>¶ A COMPLAINT TO ALMIGHTIE GOD in bitterneſſe of ſoule, of one wrapped in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerfitie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ou art my creator for thou haſte made mee, thou arte my god for I doo honour thee, O Lorde God of Hoſtes, ſhew vnto mée thy ſauynge health in the midſt of the aduerſities that haue ouerta ken mée, for whilſt I am oppreſied with woes, and erie vnto thee from the deapth of my harte, and woulde fayne aſpire with my voyce vnto the toppe of thy mercie: I am waxed faynt with féebleneſſe, my throate is become ſore, and I am nothyng the néere of helpe.</p>
            <p>Haſt thou forgotten mée, my lorde? am not I thy wretched ſeruant, and ſunne of thy handmaiden? Sumtime
<pb facs="tcp:19400:62"/>waies, in the tendreneſſe of thy moſt milde mercies withdraw thy ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, for I am alreadie feebled, layde waſt, and vtterly forlorne.</p>
            <p>Shew mée, Lorde, are my ſinnes more haynous in thy ſight, then any mans elſe, that thou haſt ſingularly plagued mée aboue the reſt? And haue I not bought déere enough my ſecret offences? Are they all pure that flowe in golde, that walke in ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, that féede on deinties, that ſléepe on downe, that abounde in poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that kéepe companie with prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that liue in all worldly wealth, and am I made poore, abiect, conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, forſaken, and caſtaway bicauſe I am only ſinfull?</p>
            <p>Turne thee, O Lorde, into my comfort, and remembre that I am but fleaſh and blood, ſet not thy might agaynſt the infirmitie of my mould, for I acknowledge that I haue ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauated the frutes of thy wrath, and
<pb facs="tcp:19400:62"/>the dayly déedes of my neclected due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ly foorth béefore my face, I cannot excuſe my ſelfe of the greateſt ſinne, there is no puniſhment that may bée made matche vnto my maliciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, it is to light whiche thou haſt layde vpon mée for mine offences.</p>
            <p>Weigh my ſorowes, O God, I call vnto thée from the botome of a broken harte, and a ſighynge ſoule, and a tormented minde, ceaſe of the ſowerneſſe of thy pretence, and mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie thy moode into mercie, conuerte my pouertie into ſufficiencie, my contempt into ſome reguarde, take from mée thy deſcrued plague that I cannot proſper, whiche ſome terme éeuell fortune, and erect mée into a place where the good giftes may bee ſeene whiche thou haſt béeſtowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon mée.</p>
            <p>It is, Lorde, a gréeuous wounde to my hart, when I béehold the good happe that ſome men haue: and how
<pb facs="tcp:19400:63"/>euery thyng goeth awrie with mee that I take in hande, not that I am ſorie at their good ſucceſſe, but it ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth mee that I finde not the like. Thei liue in good caſe in whom there is not that which reſteth in mée, they ſquare in abundance, and I lurke in want, they take their eaſe and gayne I labour and liue by the loſſe, they ſléepe and waxe ritche, I toyle and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer am poore, they ſtande ſtill and it commeth vnto them, I runne after it and ſtill it flieth from mée, I haue bin fayerly promiſed, but I ſée no perfourmance at al that enſueth, and they that ſhould doo mee good: either they cannot, or they will not, either I come to rathe, or to late vnto them or els they feede mée with ſhales and another enioyeth the frute, either they put mee of with delayes, and, O Lorde, I periſh in the meane ſeaſon.</p>
            <p>Note, my ſweete God, how vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courteouſly I haue bin dealt withal,
<pb facs="tcp:19400:63"/>for my friendſhip I haue found ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, ſutch as I haue bin principall to procure them releife: haue bin the chief cauſers to caſt mee out of my li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge, I haue bin accuſed without cauſe for that I neuer ment, I am ſuppoſed to bee other then I am, I am hit in the teeth with other mens faultes, and hard borne for things I can not mend, I am heauelie frien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of ſutch as ſhoulde fauour mee, they are readie to take from mee that which I haue: which of duetie ſhould giue mee that which I lacke, and, O God, thou knoweſt mine innocency, and how vndeſeruedly they doo it. I haue bin obedient to my power, but my portion is alotted as I had bin otherwiſe: I was borne as of thy ſeruant <hi>Sara,</hi> but I am reputed as one of the ſunnes of <hi>Agar,</hi> it were almoſt infinite to ſhew how I haue bin afflicted, and I am now oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with a burden that I cannot ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine
<pb facs="tcp:19400:64"/>ſtayne, vnleſſe thou bée my ſingular good God, and I hope herein thou wilt haue a ſpeciall reguarde vnto mée.</p>
            <p>Euer hetherto, thou haſt ſtirred vp woorthy veſſels, to relieue the woes, and cure the cares of ſutche as were wrapped in aduerſitie, &amp; haſt thou rayſed none to helpe mée, O Lorde? Surely, I do conſtantly bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue that thou wilt not leaue mée vnlooked to, although at this preſent I ſee almoſte no ſigne of ſuccour, and the welſpringes of my blood bée waxed drie towardes mée, and thou haſt multiplied the numbre of my kinneſfolkes aboue my fréeinds, and ſlender bée the twyne whereon the ſtay of my ſimple liuyng dependeth. Suffre then not to want I béeſéeche thée that haue fréeindly looked vpon my penurie, ſtande thou good Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnto them that haue dealt with mée as their naturall childe, let not
<pb facs="tcp:19400:64"/>their barnes bée y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emptier, nor their bagges the lighter, nor their houſes the deſolater, nor theyr hartes the heauier, nor their heyres the poorer, and when it ſhall pleaſe thée: then haue mée alſo in remembrance, as I ſtande not in doubt of thy gracious goodneſſe. Lorde, let my hope take effect, as the lookyng for that day he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto: hath bin cheif cauſe of the lengthnynge of this my lingrynge lothed life.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FJNIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London, in Fléet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreete by William How, dwellynge at Temple Barre.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
